<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-24T12:57:54-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nick Hunkins</title><subtitle>Nick Hunkins&apos; personal website - Powered by Jekyll and GitHub Pages</subtitle><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 2: Fundamentals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-fundamentals" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 2: Fundamentals" /><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pytorch-fundamentals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-fundamentals"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="deep-learning-with-pytorch">Deep Learning With PyTorch</h1>

<h2 id="part-2-fundamentals">Part 2: Fundamentals</h2>

<h4 id="what-is-a-tensor">What Is A Tensor?</h4>

<p>Mathematically, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensor">tensor</a> is an algebraic object that describes the relationship between its elements as it pertains to a vector space. That sounds like a lot, but it’s actualy not so complicated. You can think of a tensor as an extension of a multidimensional array where each element within the array is a vector.</p>

<p>If that’s confusing and abstract, don’t worry. We can leave the exact definition of a tensor to the mathematicians. The point is that tensors are similar to multidimensional arrays, but have a few extra perks that make them ideal for representing deep neural networks.</p>

<h4 id="tensors-in-pytorch">Tensors in PyTorch</h4>

<p>A PyTorch tensor is very similar to NumPy array. They can hold similar data structures and even share the same syntax for indexing. However, PyTorch tensors come with a couple of crucial bonus features:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Device Flexibility</strong>: Tensors can be moved easily between the CPU and GPU to optimize your workflow.</li>
  <li><strong>Autograd Support</strong>: PyTorch tensors can automatically keep track of the operations performed on them, an essential feature for backpropagation.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="note">NOTE</h3>
<p class="center"><i>While I will include sample code snippets with this post, I will not include much output. This is on purpose! The best thing to learn quickly is to try these code snippets out for yourself and see what happens!</i></p>
<p><br />
<br /></p>

<h4 id="creating-tensors">Creating Tensors</h4>

<p>Tensors can be made in multiple ways. Below are a few of the most common methods. Before we do anything, let’s import the PyTorch library</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>import torch
</code></pre></div></div>

<h5 id="scalars">Scalars</h5>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>scalar = torch.tensor(7)
</code></pre></div></div>

<h5 id="vectors">Vectors</h5>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>vector = torch.tensor([7, 7])
</code></pre></div></div>

<h5 id="matrices">Matrices</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Note that matrix variable names are capitalized by convention.</li>
</ul>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>MATRIX = torch.tensor([[7, 7],
                       [7, 7]])
</code></pre></div></div>

<h5 id="tensors-of-ones-zeros--random-values">Tensors of Ones, Zeros, &amp; Random Values</h5>
<p>We can make tensors filled with ones, zeros, or random values in a single line. All we need to do is pass in the dimensions we want of the output tensor.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ones = torch.ones(size=(3, 4))
zeros = torch.zeros(size=(1, 2, 3, 4))
random = torch.randn(size=(3, 20, 20))
</code></pre></div></div>

<h5 id="other-useful-methods---arange--like">Other Useful Methods - arange &amp; like</h5>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torch.arange(start, stop, step)</code> - Create a tensor populated with values ranging from <i>start</i> to <i>stop</i> at incrememnts of size <i>step</i></p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torch.zeros_like(input=other_tensor)</code> - Create a tensor of zeros (could be ones or randn) with the same shape as the input tensor</p>

<h4 id="working-with-tensors">Working With Tensors</h4>

<p>If tensors are going to do all the heavy lifting for our DNNs, then we better know how to work with them and how they can interact with each other. Here are some of the most common tensor operations, aggregations, and transformations. :</p>

<h5 id="common-operations">Common Operations</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Addition (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">+</code>):
    <ul>
      <li>Add a scalar to each element of a tensor or element-wise addition of two tensors of the same shape.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A + B</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A + c</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Subtraction (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-</code>):
    <ul>
      <li>Subtract a scalar from each element of a tensor or element-wise subtraction of two tensors of the same shape.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A - B</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A - c</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Multiplication (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">*</code>):
    <ul>
      <li>Multiply each element of a tensor by a scalar or element-wise multiplication of two tensors of the same shape.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A * B</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A * c</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Division (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/</code>):
    <ul>
      <li>Divide each element of a tensor by a scalar or element-wise division of two tensors of the same shape.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A / B</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A / c</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Matrix Multiplication (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@</code>):
    <ul>
      <li>Matrix multiplication between two tensors with matching inner dimensions (i.e. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[m x n] @ [n x k]</code> )</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A @ B</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torch.matmul(A, B)</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="aggregations">Aggregations</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Min
    <ul>
      <li>Return the minimum value in a tensor</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.min()</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Max
    <ul>
      <li>Return the maximum value in a tensor</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.max()</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Mean
    <ul>
      <li>Return the mean value of a tensor</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.mean()</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Sum
    <ul>
      <li>Return the sum of values in a tensor</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.sum()</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="tensor-transformations">Tensor Transformations</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Reshape
    <ul>
      <li>Reshape input tensor to specified new dimensions ()</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.reshape(9, 1)</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>View
    <ul>
      <li>Similar to reshape, but <strong>shares the same memory</strong> as the original tensor ()</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.view(9, 1)</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Permute
    <ul>
      <li>Return a view of a tensor with dmensions permuted (swapped) in a certain way</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.permute(2, 0, 1)</code> (dim0-&gt; dim1, dim2-&gt; dim0, dim1-&gt; dim2)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Stack
    <ul>
      <li>Combine multiple tensors along a specified dimension (default=0)</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torch.stack([tensor1, tensor2, tensor3])</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Squeeze
    <ul>
      <li>Removes all dimensions of size 1 from the tensor</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.squeeze()</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Unsqueeze
    <ul>
      <li>Adds a dimension of size 1 to the tensor in specified index</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tensor.unsqueeze(dim=0)</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="indexing-into-tensors">Indexing into Tensors</h4>

<p>The creators of PyTorch worked hard to ensure that their library was easy to learn if you already are familiar with other technologies in the data work world. Luckily for us, that means that if you’re comfortable slicing and dicing multidimensional arrays in NumPy, then you’ll find the same syntax works for slicing and indexing into PyTorch Tensors.</p>

<p>Consider the following tensor:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>A = [[1, 2, 3]
     [4, 5, 6]
     [7, 8, 9]]
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>Indexing
    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A[0] --&gt; tensor([1, 2, 3])</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A[0][0] --&gt; tensor(1)</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Slicing
    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A[1][0:2] --&gt; tensor([4, 5])</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="thanks">Thanks!</h4>

<p>That’s it for this whirlwind tour of the basic knowledge needed to work with tensors in PyTorch. For a deeper look, check out the <a href="https://pytorch.org/docs/stable/">Official Documentation</a> and <a href="https://pytorch.org/tutorials/beginner/ptcheat.html"> PyTorch Cheat Sheet</a>. My writing here is meant as a primer to familiarize you with essential concepts. I encourage you now (and in the future) to always check the official resources to learn more!</p>

<h3 id="continue-reading-part-3-basic-pytorch-workflow--"><a href="pytorch-workflow">Continue Reading Part 3: Basic PyTorch Workflow -&gt;</a></h3>

<h3 id="--go-back-to-part-1-a-gentle-introduction"><a href="pytorch-introduction">(&lt;- Go Back to Part 1: A Gentle Introduction)</a></h3>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 2: Fundamentals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-workflow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 2: Fundamentals" /><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pytorch-workflow</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-workflow"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="deep-learning-with-pytorch">Deep Learning With PyTorch</h1>

<h2 id="part-3-basic-pytorch-workflow">Part 3: Basic PyTorch Workflow</h2>

<h3 id="this-page-is-still-under-construction">THIS PAGE IS STILL UNDER CONSTRUCTION</h3>

<p>Utilizing a GPU (if you’ve got one)</p>
<ul>
  <li>Device agnostic code</li>
</ul>

<p>Essential PyTorch Workflow</p>

<ol>
  <li>Data</li>
  <li>Build a model</li>
  <li>Model training
    <ol>
      <li>Instantiate model</li>
      <li>Select loss function and optimizer</li>
      <li>Iterate over training data - epochs</li>
      <li>For each epoch
        <ol>
          <li>Generate predictions by calling forward() on the NN</li>
          <li>Calculate the loss using the loss function from earlier</li>
          <li>Clear the gradients from the optimizer using .zero_grad()</li>
          <li>Call backward() on loss function to calculate gradients (back propagation)</li>
          <li>Call optimizer.step() to update network weights according to calculated gradients (gradient descent)</li>
        </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Inference and evaluation</li>
  <li>Save a model</li>
</ol>

<p>Simple Example - linear model</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 1: A Gentle Introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-introduction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning With PyTorch, Part 1: A Gentle Introduction" /><published>2024-08-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pytorch-introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pytorch-introduction"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="deep-learning-with-pytorch">Deep Learning With PyTorch</h1>

<h2 id="part-1-a-gentle-introduction">Part 1: A Gentle Introduction</h2>

<p>With all the media coverage of ChatGPT and other large language models, you’re probably aware that the field of artificial intelligence is red hot these days. Indeed, the initial release and subsequent success of ChatGPT nearly two years ago sent shockwaves through the AI community and brought the technology to fore of public discussion.</p>

<p>But just how do these technologies work? After all, hasn’t AI been a topic of research and discussion for decades? Why has it just now come into prominence?</p>

<p>There are several major factors driving the success of modern AI models like ChatGPT. First, the internet and age of information has given rise to enormous amounts of data, an essential ingredient for model training. Second, modern advances in computing architecture (e.g., distributed computing) and hardware (e.g., GPUs) have made it possible to train larger and more complex models. The final driver, and the topic of this and several future posts, is the maturation of the field of <i>deep learning.</i></p>

<h4 id="what-is-deep-learning">What is Deep Learning?</h4>
<p>At a high level, deep learning is a machine learning technique that was inspired by the structure of neurons in the brain. Deep learning models are composed of layers of connected artificial neurons, mimicking how neurons connect and fire together in the brain. For this reason, deep learning networks are also referred to as neural networks. The term “deep” comes from when there are at least two layers within the network, but modern deep neural networks (DNNs) can have dozens or even hundreds of layers.</p>

<figure>  
  <img class="center" src="../assets/img/blog/pytorch/dnn.png" alt="Example DNN" />
  <figcaption>Example Deep Neural Network</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The above description of DNNs might sound too abstract to be helpful. However, the abstract nature of DNNs is exactly what makes them so powerful. It’s up to us as designers to create the DNN best suited to the problem we are trying to solve. Depending on the application, one could choose completely different components of underlying architecture (e.g., Attention, GANs, CNNs, LSTMs). Indeed, if you could open up and look inside a popular AI application like ChatGPT or Dall-E you would see a composition of these components.</p>

<h4 id="why-pytorch">Why PyTorch?</h4>
<p><a href="https://pytorch.org/">PyTorch</a> is an open source deep learning framework created by the folks over at Facebook (Meta). In recent years it has grown in popularity both in industry and academia due to its flexibility, readability, and behind-the-scenes optimization. Check out the trends over at <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/trends">paperswithcode</a> to get an idea of just how popular PyTorch has become! It’s used at Facebook, Microsoft, Tesla, and OpenAI to name a few. For this reason, PyTorch is an excellent framework in which to learn the basics of deep learning.</p>

<figure>  
  <img src="../assets/img/blog/pytorch/pytorch-trends.png" alt="pytorch trends" />
  <figcaption>PyTorch Trends (Aug 2024)</figcaption>
</figure>

<h4 id="join-me">Join Me!</h4>
<p>As I explore and learn the rich PyTorch ecosystem! Over a series of blog posts I will write about the fundamentals of PyTorch, some principles of deep learning and machine learning, and how to apply PyTorch to solve some common ML problems.</p>

<h3 id="continue-reading-part-2-pytorch-fundamentals--"><a href="pytorch-fundamentals">Continue Reading Part 2: PyTorch Fundamentals -&gt;</a></h3>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Semblance of Style</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/semblance-of-style" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Semblance of Style" /><published>2024-05-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/semblance-of-style</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/semblance-of-style"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="a-semblance-of-style">A Semblance of Style</h1>

<h3 id="the-craft-of-writing">The Craft of Writing</h3>

<p>In the last semester of my graduate schooling at the University of Colorado - Boulder, I decided to enroll in a creative writing class. I didn’t have a specific reason, but, despite the worst efforts of a couple bad English teachers in high school, I had come to truly enjoy writing as an adult. I figured it might be worthwhile (and fun!) to learn about the craft of creative writing before I stepped into the real world.</p>

<p>It turned out to be a very good decision.</p>

<p>At the start of class I was asked to write a Writer’s Statement of Purpose. In a nutshell, I was asked to summarize my relationship with writing and what I hoped to get out of the class. It was an interesting excercise that placed into perspective just how important reading and writing have been to me throughout my life.</p>

<p>I wrote about my boyhood love of the <i>Redwall</i> series, my discovery of journaling in my early twenties, and my rediscovered love of fiction in more recent years. I mentioned some authors that had influenced me, like Kurt Vonnegut, Sylvia Plath, Ernest Hemingway, Herman Hesse, and David Foster Wallace, and I lamented the restricted style of all the technical writing I had done, specifically how its influence self-consciously stiffened my prose.</p>

<p>The subtext of the whole statement can be summarized as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have circuitously discovered the importance of reading and writing on the personal, interpersonal, and societal levels. With this knowledge in mind, I want to develop my own writing ability so that I can more deeply engage with this world. That is, I want to find my voice.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now, at the conclusion of the creative writing class, I’m happy to say that I did find my voice, or at least, I’ve begun to uncover it. I like to think of it as an instrument. Occassionally it’s out of tune or a bit raspy, and sometimes it doesn’t quite convey the melody it tries to carry, but it is still my voice, and mine alone. And, when it does strike the right notes and rhythms, it rings clear and sharp. In those rare moments, I feel a very deep sense of wholesome satisfaction.</p>

<p>Of course, I still have much to learn (as is true of anybody of any skill in any craft) and I will never be perfect. I’m sure some will complain of my sentence structure or my comma usage. But I stubbornly refuse to let the fear of imperfection be an obstacle to the development of my writing. I’m going to write, and god dammit I’m going to share it despite its flaws. There is no better way to improve than to try your best, share it with others, and learn from the feedback.</p>

<p>With all that said, I have spent a few hours rereading and reflecting on what I wrote this past semester. Below I tease out three features of what I believe to be my nascent writing style. I’d like to write the remainder of this statement as if I were teaching these three things to my future self, just in case I should forget!</p>

<h3 id="1-write-what-is-meaningful">1. Write What Is Meaningful</h3>

<p>First and foremost, write what is meaningful. You might ask, ”what do you mean by meaningful?” and that is indeed a good question! Meaning lies in the hidden truths of our everyday life. It’s the smell of a fresh cup of coffee on a Sunday morning, the pure joy of throwing a rubber ball to a gleeful dog, the glimpse of a bird flying overhead and out of sight. These moments are too often treated as mere filler between the “real” parts of life, but this is all wrong. If we cannot experience these simple moments fully for what they are, then we are missing out on our own life, and that is an unthinkable tragedy.</p>

<p>Of course, meaning lies in the big truths, too! Too often the most obvious truths go unnoticed or unappreciated. For example, I have gotten older since I started writing this, and I will never get that time back again, because like it or not, I am always aging. I am always choosing how to spend my limited time on this earth, and the truth is, I never have known nor will I ever know exactly how much time I have left. I know this on some level, but on another level, I’m in denial about it, or I forget about it, and that is exactly what makes for an interesting and important piece of writing.</p>

<p>Obviously, I cannot in just a few short paragraphs answer the age old question of “what is meaningful?” I’m not attempting to take on such a stupid task, and I don’t believe there is a single answer to the question. In my opinion, meaning is everywhere, but you have to refine it a little bit before it’s worth anything. What I’ve described above is some territory in my life where the raw stuff bubbles up a little more readily.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, I don’t give a shit about writing something unless it can gesture to something meaningful, and I’d be wise to remember that.</p>

<h3 id="2-write-only-what-is-essential">2. Write Only What Is Essential</h3>

<p>Second, write only what is essential. I once lamented an episode in my undergraduate days where I enrolled in “Writing for Engineers.” The class emphasized concise, clear writing, and discouraged all else. If math could be converted to language, this was what it would look like. After taking this course I complained that “the whole project turned my insides gray.” However, throughout the past few months I’ve changed my mind on this. I’ve written a lot of technical writing since taking that class way back in 2014, and after taking this creative writing class, I’ve realized just how strong my writing fundamentals are as a result. The whole point of technical writing is to convey what must be said and then to move on. This writing tendency manifests itself in my writing in a few, useful ways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>My work has detail, but is not overwritten. I don’t waste time describing how the light trickles through the canopy to rain down on the bushes below. Well, I will write that, but then I’ll move on. You see the forest? You see the sunshine? How about the bushes? Okay, you get the picture. Let’s keep going.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My work doesn’t get stuck. There’s no purpose in including something that doesn’t have purpose. Either it’s essential to the piece or it’s superfluous. If it doesn’t do any work for the direction of the piece, then it doesn’t belong in the piece.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My work conveys something. If the piece doesn’t have a direction, then it isn’t ready to be written. It doesn’t need to be perfectly thought out in advance, but if it meanders around without purpose then the reader will get bored, and that is the worst case scenario.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>My work has detail, it has summary, it doesn’t get stuck or overwritten, and it always conveys something. This is only my opinion, but it’s the honest one that I have. My initial chagrin at all that time spent in the weeds of technical writing has turned to gratitude for the skillset it has given me.</p>

<h3 id="3-write-with-humor-and-honesty">3. Write With Humor and Honesty</h3>

<p>The third point is to write with humor and honesty. I couple humor and honesty together because I find the two so often go hand-in-hand.</p>

<p>The virtue of honesty is obvious. You’ll sound like an idiot if you don’t know what you’re talking about, and even if you were to successfully bullshit your way out of overt idiocy, the writing itself is no less insincere. Maybe others can make something useful out of that, but not me, and I doubt I’d respect the words of anything that emerged from such a process. Further, honestly requires serious self-reflection. You cannot be honest unless you know what you think, and if you don’t know what you think, then your writing will reflect that. Good writing requires honesty.</p>

<p>However, honesty quickly turns boring without a good dose of levity, and that’s why humor is so important. I don’t want to pour facts onto a page, I want to convey something meaningful, and humor can act as a wonderful lubricant to deliver that message. Note that I do not mean humor in the sense of being carefree or frivolous. No, that would be to denigrate the whole purpose of writing! Why write anything if it doesn’t matter? Nor do I mean that the piece <i>must</i> be funny. Sure, if it is funny, that’s great! However, I’m not a comedian, I’m a writer. What I mean is that the writing should be sincere, but not take itself too seriously. Life is short. Life is complicated. Everybody is tangled in a personal web of contradictions while sipping a cocktail of inherited bullshit. What I have to say may be insightful or useful or entertaining, but it’s also just a bunch of words from some guy upside down in a web sipping on his own cocktail.</p>

<p>Good writing should make you feel or think something real, but it should go down easily, too. The best meals are healthy <i>and</i> tasty.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>So there they are, the three takeaways for me to carry off into my writing future: write what is meaningful, write only what is essential, and write with humor and honesty. What comes next for me? I’m transitioning out of school and back into the workforce. I’m not exactly sure what the future of my writing looks like, but I know that I’ll still be writing every day. Whether it’s work emails, blog posts (like this one), presentations, journal entries, or messages to loved ones, I can use the lessons I’ve learned from this semester to be a better communicator of ideas. Time will tell how my skills will be used, but used they shall be.</p>

<p>I’d like to close by referencing the final line of my initial Writer’s Statement of Purpose that I wrote back in January. “I’ve mentioned several of my literary heroes above, and if I could become just 1% more like any of them, then I’d consider myself a writer.” By experimenting with style, by putting effort into writing and rewriting and rewriting again, and by developing some semblance of a personal style, I can honestly say that I have achieved that goal.</p>

<p>I can honestly call myself a writer.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clifton Strengths Assessment: My Top 5 Strengths</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/clifton-top5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clifton Strengths Assessment: My Top 5 Strengths" /><published>2024-04-19T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/clifton-top5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/clifton-top5"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />

  <style>
    table, th, td {
      table-layout: fixed;
      border: 1px solid;
      padding: 5px;
      width: 100%;
      margin-left: auto;
      margin-right: auto;
    }
  </style>
</head>

<h1 id="clifton-strengths-assessment--my-top-5-strengths">Clifton Strengths Assessment: <br /> My Top 5 Strengths</h1>

<h4 id="yet-another-personality-assessment">Yet Another Personality Assessment</h4>

<p>I’ve taken quite a few online personality tests. I learned about my accountability style with Gretchen Rubin’s Four Tendencies assessment. I learned about my psychological personality traits by taking the Big 5 questionnaire. I even know which Harry Potter house the sorting hat would place me, and I’m not even much of a Harry Potter fan!</p>

<p>Indeed, there is something fun when it comes to learning about ourselves, and that’s about as much stock as I placed into the world of personality assessments. They’re something fun and curious, but after the initial wave of novelty wears off, the results melt from my brain and dribble out of my ears.</p>

<p>This was my attitude when I recently took the <a href="https://www.gallup.com/cliftonstrengths/en/252137/home.aspx">Clifton Strengths Assessment</a> by Gallup. I got the opportunity to take the Clifton Strengths Assessment for free through my work with the <a href="https://www.postinternetproject.org">Post-Internet Project</a>, and after some initial resistance I agreed to give it a try. So, one morning last week, I brewed a cup of hot coffee and sat down at my desk to begin.</p>

<h4 id="the-clifton-strengths-assessment">The Clifton Strengths Assessment</h4>

<p>Right away I noticed that this assessment felt different from the ones I had taken before for two reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The questions were presented on a likert scale without an obvious direction towards “better” or “worse”</li>
  <li>The assessment asks that you answer the question with your first instinct, hiding the question if you took too long to answer.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="../assets/img/blog/clifton-top5/example-question.png" /></p>

<p>Combined, these two qualities encouraged a sense of honesty from me. I couldn’t game the system, and I couldn’t overthink it. I must admit that I was intrigued to see what sort of results would come out of the answers I was giving, and, in just about thirty minutes, I had them.</p>

<h2 id="my-clifton-top-5-strengths">My Clifton Top 5 Strengths</h2>

<p><img src="../assets/img/blog/clifton-top5/top5.png" /></p>

<p><br />
The results I got from the assessment deeply resonated with my own sense of who I am, which was unexpected! I know it may seem stupid to be surprised that a personality test accurately captured some features of my personality, but after so many “meh” results from other tests, this one truly felt… well, surprising!</p>

<ol>
  <li><span style="color:green;"><b>Ideation</b><i>(Strategic Thinking):</i></span> I love ideas! I love learning about new ones or thinking about the same ole stuff in new exciting ways. My favorite conversations are the ones situated around ideas, and when a new idea connects other concepts that previously seemed unrelated... oh yeah, that's my jam.</li>
  <br />
  <li><span style="color:blue;"><b>Adaptability</b> <i>(Relationship Building):</i></span> I've always been a "go with the flow" kind of guy (occasionally to a fault). You never know where a flow might take you. After all, change is inevitable, surprises are wonderful, and, as they say, variety is the spice of life.</li>
  <br />
  <li><span style="color:green;"><b>Intellection</b> <i>(Strategic Thinking):</i></span> What resonates most here is introspection and reflection, which are absolutely invaluable to me. The great task of life is to know thyself, and to know thyself one must study oneself. (And, as Dogen said, to study the self is to forget the self, but that's for another post).</li>
  <br />
  <li><span style="color:blue;"><b>Developer</b> <i>(Relationship Building):</i></span> In my adult life I've really come to appreciate the importance of other people in one's own journey of personal growth. Other people can help you grow in ways you didn't think possible, and you can do the same for them.</li>
  <br />
  <li><span style="color:purple;"><b>Restorative</b> <i>(Executing):</i></span> Problem solving is how I make a living. I've always enjoyed the activity of it, from fixing broken appliances to playing word games to <a href="projects/optimizing-hadoop-ingests">optimizing ingests into a Hadoop cluster</a>.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-deeper-look">A Deeper Look</h2>

<p>Upon first impression, these strengths all feel true to myself, but what else do they say? Are there some nuggets of wisdom that I can use to improve myself, my work, and/or my relationships? I was sent some more imformation about each of these strengths by a friend of mine, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aiineducation/">Adnan Iftekhar</a>. Below I present and synthesize some of this information.</p>

<h3 id="1-descriptive-words">1. Descriptive Words</h3>

<p class="center" style="text-align:center">
<b><span style="color:green;">Ideation</span></b>
<br />
Spontaneous, Creative, Innovative, Collaborative, Artistic, Insightful, Resourceful, Stimulating
<br />
<br />
<b><span style="color:blue;">Adaptability</span></b>
<br />
Flexible, Responsive, Easy-going, Present, In the moment, Spontaneous, Agreeable, Existential
<br />
<br />
<b><span style="color:green;">Intellection</span></b>
<br />
Introspective, Solitary, Intellectual, Philosophical, In-depth, Reflective, Discontent, Thinking, Intense, Musing, Driven 
<br />
<br />
<b><span style="color:blue;">Developer</span></b>
<br />
Patient, Perceptive, Effective, Encouraging, Investing, Others-orientated, Observant, Growth-orientated, Self-sacrificing, Helpful 
<br />
<br />
<b><span style="color:purple;">Restorative</span></b>
<br />
Problem-orientated, Driven, Investigative, Weakness-orientated, Responsive, Unintimidated, Insightful 
</p>

<h3 id="2-needs--production">2. Needs &amp; Production</h3>
<p class="center" style="text-align: center; width: 80%;"><i>What a given strength needs to function and what it can produce.</i></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">Strength</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Needs</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Produces</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Ideation</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Freedom to explore possibilities without restraints or limitations.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">New and fresh perspectives.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Adaptability</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Present pressures that demand an immediate response.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">A willingness to follow the lead of change.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Intellection</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Time for reflection and meditation.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Depth of understanding and wisdom.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Developer</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Someone to invest in.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">A commitment (time and energy) to human growth.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:purple;">Restorative</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Problems that must be solved.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Courage and creativity to problematic situations.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />
<i>Synthesis</i></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What I need most is the freedom to explore, concrete problems to solve, meaningful relationships, and solitude for reflection. If I have these things, then I can bring a creative perspective to the challenges that most need solving, and I can temper this creativity with wisdom, understanding, and compassion.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="3-motivation--demotivation">3. Motivation &amp; Demotivation</h3>
<p class="center" style="text-align: center; width: 80%;"><i>What motivates and demotivates a given strength.</i></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">Strength</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Motivating</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Demotivating</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Ideation</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Coming up with something brand new.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Doing what we’ve always done.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Adaptability</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Spontaneity.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Predictability.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Intellection</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">The theoretical because it is the precursor to the practical.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">A thoughtless approach to anything.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Developer</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Human potential and progress.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Wasted or unrealised potential.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:purple;">Restorative</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Finding solutions.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">The idea that problems will disappear if they are ignored.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />
<i>Synthesis</i></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How can I motivate myself to meet the needs I described above? I should keep my love of building something new at the forefront of my awareness. Further, I should remember how important it is to me to bring out the best in myself and others, and to not be afraid to think too abstractly. Finally, I should avoid dull routine and embrace novel ways of living and working.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="4-balcony--basement">4. Balcony &amp; Basement</h3>
<p class="center" style="text-align: center; width: 80%;"><i>The best and worst instantiation of a given strength.</i></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">Strength</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Balcony</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Basement</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Ideation</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Improves on the existing, learns quickly, agile mind</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Serendipitous, lacks follow-through, creates more work, always something new, never satisfied</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Adaptability</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Flexible, comfortable in times of change, easy to get along with, goes with the flow.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Directionless, indecisive, sheep, inconclusive, whimsical.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Intellection</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Excellent thinker, enjoys musing, capable of deep and philosophical thought, able to work alone.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">A loner, slow to act or wastes time thinking too much, isolated, doesn’t work well with others.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Developer</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Grows talent in others, teacher, coach, enjoys helping others succeed, invest in others.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Not an individual contributor, wastes time on low-potential people, spectator.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:purple;">Restorative</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Problem solver, trouble shooter, finds improvements and solutions.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Focuses on weaknesses, punitive, negative, critical.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />
<i>Synthesis</i></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The balcony and basement descriptions seem to serve as guideposts in successfully developing these strengths and warning signs when things may be going off the rails.
<br />
<span style="color:green;"><b>Guideposts:</b> </span>Reward myself for improving on existing things, learning new material, and building up others, especially if I do these things with a sense of flexibility. 
<br />
<span style="color:red;"><b>Warnings:</b> </span>Watch out for those times when tempted to take on a new project. Specifically, examine my motivations for the new project and bias towards completing existing projects before taking on anything new. Additionally, be wary of overthinking, indecisiveness, and negativity, as they may be symptoms of a lack of clarity or conviction. Finally, I need to really value my own time, being careful to give it only to those who most deserve it.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="5-raw--mature">5. Raw &amp; Mature</h3>
<p class="center" style="text-align: center; width: 80%;"><i>The underdeveloped and mature version of a given strength.</i></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">Strength</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Raw</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Mature</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Ideation</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Fascinated with fantasy.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Imagination to innovate and improve reality.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Adaptability</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Short attention span.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Intense awareness to respond with immediacy.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:green;">Intellection</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">The need for introspection leads to isolation.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Deep self-reflection is a prelude to deep conversation.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Developer (1)</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">The key to growth is to invest in myself.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">The key to growth is to invest in others.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:blue;">Developer (2)</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">All potential is equally important.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Wisely chooses in whom to invest.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong><span style="color:purple;">Restorative</span></strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Has an eye for what’s wrong, but lacks solution or effort to fix it.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">Sees brokenness and contributes to healing.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />
<i>Synthesis</i></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The raw and mature distinction seems to distinguish between what only appears to be a healthy strength and an truly healthy strength. In a certain sense, it’s striking a balance where a strength is cultivated fully, but not taken too far. Underlying each balancing point is the necessity of strong awareness and concentration, without which no balance could be struck. I would be wise to do the following:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Imagine big, but stay grounded in reality.</li>
    <li>Reflect deeply on life, but be willing to share it with others.</li>
    <li>Invest in others, but be wise in the choice of whom to invest.</li>
    <li>Recognize what isn’t working, but don’t hold back in fixing it.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="takeaway">Takeaway</h2>

<p>According to Gallup, the Clifton Strengths Assessment results are very stable over time, meaning that the results I’ve posted here should be relevant for my personal and professional life for years to come. With that in mind, it seems pertinent to nail down what I can carry forward with me into the future. For this, I’d like to summarize what I’ve learned about my top five strengths with respect to three domains of life: self, work, and other. I imagine each of these domains as petals out of a spiritual center, my personal spiritual practice being Zen Buddhism.</p>

<p><br />
<img src="../assets/img/blog/clifton-top5/three-domains.png" class="center" />
<br /></p>

<p>A strong sense of awareness and concentration is necessary to live well. That is, they are necessary to ensure that ones thought, speech, and action come from a place of clarity and wisdom. Therefore, a precursor to all of what follows is this:</p>

<p class="center" style="color:black;text-align:center;font-size:25px;"><i><b>Maintain a strong Zen practice.</b></i></p>

<h4 id="self">Self</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Intentionally set aside regular time for solitude and reflection.</li>
  <li>Experiment with new ways of working and living. Avoid dull, pointless routine.</li>
  <li>Beware overthinking, indecision, and negativity. Seek clarity and conviction.</li>
  <li>Reward yourself for desirable behavior.</li>
  <li>Imagine big, but stay grounded in reality.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="work">Work</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Make room to explore potential solutions before committing to one.</li>
  <li>Look for existing things to improve upon and concrete problems to solve.</li>
  <li>Remember your love for learning and building things.</li>
  <li>Be very picky about taking on new projects. Carefully examine your “why.”</li>
  <li>Try your very best, but be adaptable and humorous in times of adversity.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="other">Other</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Invest 80% of your social time into a few meaningful relationships.</li>
  <li>Look for ways to bring out the best in others. Actualize good for others.</li>
  <li>Remember how good it feels to positively impact somebody elses life.</li>
  <li>Be very picky in your friends. Look for potential, and avoid the cynics.</li>
  <li>Be vulnerable and courageous with your friends. Share deeply and honestly.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>To wrap this up in the proverbial bow, I want to set an intention with how to use the knowledge that I’ve synthesized here. I’m not typically one for checklists and rules, so setting some simple “read this over once a day” heuristic doesn’t hold much appeal to me. However, there is an unavoidable truth in learning: memory requires repetition. So, I’m going to make some flashcards for the bullet points I listed above and keep them on my desk for a while. Flashcards are old school, but damn are they effective. After a few weeks these gems should be firmly lodged in my memory, and after a few months (assuming I’m practicing what I’m memorizing) they should be second nature.</p>

<p>This post has been entirely about me, Nick, the author. If you read the whole thing, great! Thanks for your time and attention. Even though this has been an exercise in my own personal growth, I hope you found something useful or interesting to you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Merits of Walking Really, Really Far</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Merits of Walking Really, Really Far" /><published>2024-04-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-04-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="on-the-merits-of-walking-really-really-far">On the Merits of <br />Walking Really, Really Far</h1>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<i>Walking, ideally, is a state in which the mind, the body, and the world are aligned, as though they were three characters finally in conversation together, three notes suddenly making a chord. Walking allows us to be in our bodies and in the world without being made busy by them.</i>”</p>
  <blockquote>
    <blockquote>
      <p>Rebecca Solnit, <i>Wanderlust: A History of Walking</i></p>
    </blockquote>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="the-triple-crown">The Triple Crown</h4>

<p>It was a warm and sunny September day in Rhododendron, Oregon when Adam and Kylie pulled their rented Subaru into a dusty gravel parking lot. They woke in the dark of the early morning to catch a plane from Denver to Portland, and the interim 45 miles of highway from Portland International Airport were driven in a state of quiet anticipation. Just over a month ago, Kylie was standing atop Mt. Katahdin deep in the wilderness of central Maine. She had just finished the last of the three long trails she needed to complete one of the most prestigious achievements in the world of thru-hiking: The Triple Crown. Alongside her stood her partner Adam. He had completed his Triple Crown less than a year before and came to join Kylie for the last few hundred miles of her effort. It was a moment neither of them would ever forget, and now, a few weeks later, they were sitting in a dusty parking lot in Rhododendron outside the venue of the Triple Crown Ceremony, the magnificent Mt. Hood standing proudly in the distance.</p>

<p>The Triple Crown is composed of three long trails situated across the breadth of the United States. In the West lies the beautiful Pacific Crest Trail, which is 2,600 miles long starting in California and ending in Washington. The Continental Divide Trail, right down the center of the Rocky Mountains, is 3,100 miles stretching from New Mexico to Montana. Finally, in the East sits the Appalachian Trail. It’s the shortest of the three at 2,200 miles long from Georgia to Maine, but widely considered the most challenging in terms of weather and trail quality. Together, these three behemoths add up to nearly 8,000 miles in length and constitute the Holy Grail of thru-hiking. Each one takes an average of over a 100 days to complete, meaning that if one chooses to commit to doing all three they are committing to nearly a year out of doors carrying equipment up and down mountainsides. It’s no wonder that only the most dedicated and masochistic of thru-hikers go for this achievement.</p>

<h4 id="the-world-of-thru-hiking">The World of Thru-hiking</h4>

<p>You may have guessed by now that thru-hiking might require a certain type of personality. Indeed, it does have a reputation of being a world for misfits, and if you boil the activity down to its component parts, it’s a wonder that anybody chooses to do it at all. Who would want to carry a bunch of heavy and expensive equipment on their back and then trek into the wilderness for weeks on end without pay? Such a person would spend all day sweating up steep inclines and pulverizing their knees into powder on long, meandering descents. They’d sweat in the sun, get drenched in the rain, and shiver in the snow. They’d have to ration food and filter all of their water – that is, whenever they could find water. And at the end of the day, they wouldn’t get to shower and sleep in a soft bed. No, they’d crawl into a dirty sleeping bag and sleep in their accrued daily filth and sweat on the hard ground. Oh, and did I mention that there are no bathrooms out in the wilderness? Even something as simple as relieving oneself turns into work, something to be planned and executed.</p>

<p>Indeed, many people who attempt thru-hiking promptly give up! Nearly a third of those who start the Appalachian Trail with full intent to stand on top of Mt. Katahdin quit within the first 100 miles, and another third quit within the first 500. And yet, there remains the few that do make it all the way to Maine. These are members of a subculture that live to live outside. When they’re on the trail, they feel alive, and when they’re not, they’re thinking about when they will be back on the trail. Kylie and Adam are squarely in this latter group, as are the others in attendance at the Triple Crown Ceremony.</p>

<p>Amongst fellow thru-hikers, Kylie and Adam go by their trail names: Tang and Chipotle. A trail name is a funny, sacred thing. One’s given name is for the real world, but on trail, the real world is so distant that it may as well be ancient Mesopotamia. Out on trail one needs a different name for different circumstances. Trail names can be chosen or given, and they can be anything! Commonly, they are bestowed by a companion who notices some personality quirk or witnesses some funny or strange happening. The aptly monikered Chipotle earned his title from his love of the chain restaurant of the same name. Chipotle estimates that he’s eaten Chipotle no less than 2000 times, and every time a new store opens up he is one of the first to try it out. Other trail names aren’t so obvious. The origin of Tang’s trail name remains a mystery to most of those who know her, and she likes it that way. Shades, Sticks, Boomerang, All-You-Can-Eat, Double-Stuff, Longfish, Church, Thoroughbred, Scab, and Dirty-Girl are all names that invite speculation of epics and comedies. Kylie and Adam were happy to be in this room, among these people, and with them felt a deep sense of camaraderie. These people all got each other. They’ve seen what’s out there in the wilderness, and they understand why it’s worth pursuing.</p>

<h4 id="walking-around-science-history--culture">Walking Around: Science, History, &amp; Culture</h4>

<p>Thru-hikers aren’t the only ones who have found something profound walking through the wilderness. Indeed, there is a long history of folks who found purpose along their walks in nature. Jean-Jaques Rousseau, Henry David Thoreau, William Wordsworth, Virginia Woolf, Charles Darwin, John Muir, and countless others discovered that walking through the woods could be a source of great inspiration and clarity – a way to not only know the world better, but to know oneself better, too. Reflect on your own life, dear reader. You yourself have probably at least once “gone on a walk to clear your head.” In recent years there has been growing scientific interest in the important relationship between the mind and the feet. Researchers have found that walking for as little as 90 minutes a week can decrease cognitive decline in elderly women, that walking for an hour on a treadmill prior to a divergent thinking test improved creativity scores by 60%, and that regular periods of walking can even increase the volume of the hippocampus, the brain’s memory center. The fact that walking, a simple, non-cognitive task, has such a wealth of benefits for our brain health is on its surface quite surprising. However, the story begins to make much more sense when we consider our ancient ancestors.</p>

<p>Evolutionary biologists have much to say on walking and the brain, and many have gone so far as to credit our bipedalism as a necessary precursor to our high intelligence. The use of two legs rather than four, the thinking goes, resulted in two important changes in our evolutionary history: the development of our hands and more efficient ambulation. The development of hands entailed the development of complex manipulation – the exact kind of skill that required the use of cortical tissue, the brain matter associated with complex thought and reasoning. Additionally, more efficient ambulation meant that excess energy could be devoted to the brain rather than musculature. Together, these changes formed a virtuous cycle. As our brains grew, we developed new skills and tools, like hunting and language. As our skills and tools developed, our species developed more efficient methods of collecting and storing resources. An excess amount of resources meant more energy could be devoted to the brain and its development. And so on. Summed up by the evolutionary biologist Mary Leaky,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><i>“One cannot overemphasize the role of bipedalism in hominid development. It stands as perhaps the salient point that differentiates the forebears of man from other primates. This unique ability freed the hands for myriad possibilities - carrying, tool-making, intricate manipulation. From this single development, in fact, stems all modern technology. Somewhat oversimplified, the formula holds that this new freedom of forelimbs posed a challenge. The brain expanded to meet it. And mankind was formed.”</i></p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="hiking-as-a--whole-human">Hiking as a  Whole Human</h4>

<p>Of course, none of this was on the minds of Kylie or Adam as they traded trail stories with the other Triple Crowners in that stuffy room in Rhododendron. Their brains may have benefited from the thousands of miles they spent walking trails, but brain health wasn’t ever on the list of reasons why they chose to hike thousands and thousands of miles. To them, being on trail was a way of life, something that was deeply challenging and fulfilling, something that simply wasn’t available in their day-to-day lives back home.</p>

<p>Thru-hiking engenders a clarity of purpose that has become all-too-rare in the modern world. When you wake in the morning nestled in your sleeping bag, early morning sun illuminating your colorful nylon cocoon, there is a very clear idea of what needs to be done, and that simplifies life to a delightful degree. What will you eat today? Whatever you have in your bag. How far will you walk? However far you need to go.  Who will you walk with? Whoever is walking in the same direction you are. Beyond these questions remain a few points of uncertainty, such as the afternoon weather or the quality of trail in the upcoming national forest, but life on trail takes on a quality of streamlined unity – something notably lacking in much of modernity. As observed by the author Rebecca Solnit over twenty years ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><i>“Many people nowadays live in a series of interiors - home, car, gym, office, shops - disconnected from each other. On foot everything stays connected, for while walking one occupies the spaces between those interiors in the same way one occupies those interiors. One lives in the whole world rather than in interiors built up against it.”</i></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Far from a series of interiors, longer trails are broken apart into segments between trailheads or county roads. However, when you ask a thru-hiker to remember their time on trail they’ll typically recall their experience on trail in terms of stories. After spending so much time walking through wilderness, something interesting is bound to happen.</p>

<p>That afternoon in Rhododendron, a series of guest speakers shared some of their trail stories. A well-known thru-hiker named Rascal shared a personal anecdote from his time spent on the CDT. He described how he had lost his toilet paper right out of town just before a very remote part of the trail, so he had to use rocks to wipe himself for three days before finally encountering another hiker who mercifully donated some of his supplies to him. Later, a woman named Fidget spoke about her seven year hike from the southernmost tip of South America to the northernmost tip of North America - a 22,000 mile epic filled with stories of terror, compassion, and triumph. The stories shared made the room laugh, gasp, and even brought some to tears, yet so many others went untold. Each and every one of the hikers in the room that day had their own stories, their own experiences, their own lessons learned, but most would never be shared outside the circles of a few close friends and hiking partners.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion-really-why-thru-hike">Conclusion: Really, Why Thru-hike?</h4>

<p>At nearly 8,000 miles in length, it takes some people their whole lives to complete the Triple Crown, while others make the (insane) attempt to complete it in a single year. Regardless of pace, it is an unbelievably impressive achievement, and it is no wonder that fewer than 700 people to date have officially completed it – about as many people who have been to space. At the conclusion of the ceremony, small wooden plaques were awarded to 2023’s batch of Triple Crowners. Adam and Kylie collected their plaques, returned home to Colorado, and displayed their awards next to each other on a small shelf in their bedroom. They do not show them off to guests, and they do not brag about their Triple Crowner status. Indeed, there’s something important about how such a small token can represent such an enormous achievement. There is a temptation here to allude to the old expression: “The journey of a thousand miles begins with a single step,” but this is obvious, and it doesn’t fully capture the point I want to make.</p>

<p>What does one get out of thru-hiking? It certainly cannot be the little piece of decorated wood awarded at the Triple Crown ceremony, because, if so, what a ripoff that would be! So, is it strong legs and a healthy respiratory system? Or, is it the epic stories of getting caught in thunderstorms or running out of water on a long, dry stretch of trail? Could it be the deep friendships that form in the collective overcoming of true adversity? I think these are all wonderful rewards from thru-hiking, but there’s something more. It’s also the experience of startling an angry bull moose from a nap and taking shelter in a grove of trees until it leaves you unharmed. It’s laying stock still in your tent trying not to make a sound as a large animal sniffs around your campsite in the darkness. It’s getting into town after being in the mountains for eight days and gleefully gorging yourself on a full stack of pancakes drenched in syrup. It’s standing on a mountaintop as the sun breaks over the horizon, bathing the world in the first light of a day that has not come before, that will not come again, and that you, by some miraculous stroke of pure luck, are alive to witness. These are not moments you can buy, they are not moments you can plan for, and they are not moments you can hold onto. In an era where we feel constant pressure to move faster, plan better, and to make absolutely sure that our lives unfold by our own design, thru-hiking stands in resolute opposition. It is a world in which life moves at its own pace, in its own way, and with its own surprises. In a certain sense, thru-hiking requires more living than our day-to-day lives do. And to experience it, all you have to do is walk.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<figure>  
  <img class="center" src="../assets/img/blog/adam-and-kylie.png" alt="Adam (Chipotle) and Kylie (Tang)" />
  <figcaption>Adam (Chipotle) and Kylie (Tang)</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<p>Oppezzo, Marily, and Daniel L. Schwartz. “Give your ideas some legs: the positive effect of walking on creative thinking.” Journal of experimental psychology: learning, memory, and cognition 40.4 (2014): 1142.</p>

<p>Voss, Michelle W., et al. “Plasticity of brain networks in a randomized intervention trial of exercise training in older adults.” Frontiers in aging neuroscience 2 (2010): 32.</p>

<p>Weuve, Jennifer, et al. “Physical activity, including walking, and cognitive function in older women.” Jama 292.12 (2004): 1454-1461.</p>

<p>Erickson, Kirk I., et al. “Exercise training increases size of hippocampus and improves memory.” Proceedings of the national academy of sciences 108.7 (2011): 3017-3022.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection On Just Starting Out</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection On Just Starting Out" /><published>2024-04-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="reflection-on-just-starting-out">Reflection On Just Starting Out</h1>

<h4 id="the-return-home">The Return Home</h4>

<p>I remember stepping off the jetway into Lambert Airport in St. Louis, MO. The feeling was surreal. It was March of 2017 and I had just spent the last 13 months teaching English in South Korea.</p>

<p>The feeling of coming back home was a complicated one, a swirling mixture of sadness for the end of an amazing journey and excitement for the beginning of a new one. Soon I would see my family members who had been mere faces on a screen for the past year. Soon I would see my friends and learn about what they had been up to since I’d been gone. Soon I would be broke.</p>

<p>While Korea was a life-changing experience, it certainly was not a profitable one. I had a few thousand dollars saved. It was enough to last me four months if I stretched, but I needed more. I needed a job.</p>

<h4 id="launchcode">LaunchCode</h4>

<p>Luckily for me I had wisely chosen to study math and computer science in college, so I actually had a foundation of technical skills that could be cultivated to start a career. Plus, while I had been overseas I started to read about this new thing called “Data Science.” I wasn’t really sure what it meant exactly (I still wonder sometimes), but I knew it involved working with math, machine learning, and computers. Naturally, I was intrigued, so I began studying a little bit each day before going to work.</p>

<p>When I came back home I learned about a non-profit organization called <a href="https://www.launchcode.org/">LaunchCode</a> through a friend of mine. Their mission was to get people working in tech based on their skills rather than their degrees. I put together a couple of sample projects to show what I could do and applied to their program. I was overjoyed when they accepted my application. Eventually they offered to place me in a 90-day internship in a new data science team at Graybar Electric, and I happily accepted!</p>

<h4 id="graybar">Graybar</h4>

<p>Those first few months at Graybar were spent cutting my teeth on code and collaboration. What I learned most during that time was just how different industry work operated compared to academic work. There weren’t any classes or grades or clubs. There was just our team and the projects that the team needed to get done.</p>

<p>I loved collaborating with others on difficult problems, and I could tell that I was learning quickly. I was lucky to find myself among a young and scrappy team, made up of other people like me who wanted to learn and prove they could do this kind of work well. It was composed of misfits who had tried their hand in some other discipline before pivoting into the exciting new field of data science, and at the head of this motley crew was my boss, Jeremy Salazar, who was the scrappiest of us all.</p>

<p>I truly enjoyed those first months working at Graybar, and I guess I proved something to them, because they offered me a job at the end of the internship. Less than 6 months after coming home, I had started a career in data science.</p>

<h4 id="gratitude">Gratitude</h4>

<p>As I write about this time in my life, I’m overcome with a sense of gratitude for having gotten the chances that have gotten me to where I am today. I was the beneficiary of the opportunities presented by Korea, LaunchCode, and Graybar, and I will always be grateful for having received them. After working at Graybar for a few years, another opportunity presented itself. I moved to Boulder, CO to begin a graduate education in Computer Science, but that’s for another post.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help" /><published>2024-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="the-less-helpful-side-of-self-help">The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help</h1>

<h4 id="avoiding-the-self-help-trap">Avoiding the Self-help Trap</h4>

<p>Self-help is a popular genre for a reason. Nobody knows you better than yourself, so you require some help, why not take ownership over that process? This sounds great on its surface, but there is a pernicious side-effect to this project.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong. Good things can come out of good self-help books. I’m grateful for having spent the time and energy to learn from books like Atomic Habits, Time Management for Mortals, and Deep Work, just to name a few. Smart people have smart ideas, who would have thought? In addition to the ideas themselves, reading self-help books can be deeply inspirational! You can have a better life, and here’s a new way to do it! Isn’t it wonderful to imagine? But, as is so often the case, there’s a dark side to this hopeful venture.</p>

<h4 id="problem-1-who-are-you">Problem 1: Who are you?</h4>
<p>Imagine that you’ve just purchased a self-help book at your local bookstore. Before you’ve even flipped open the cover, you’ve already made an implicit assumption: I need help, and this book has answers. With your purchase you have assumed a vulnerable mental stance and allotted the author a certain amount of trust.</p>

<p>This is a mistake. By design the book is written for a general audience – a general recipe for the average reader of the rough demographic the book was meant to target in its inception. The text may speak with authority, but its target audience is a caricature where you are a fully-fleshed human being.</p>

<p>The common strategy these books deploy is to simplify problems and then assert their correctness. In other words, they approach their reader with bravado and conveniently ignore the complexities of individual circumstances, the very complexities that give rise to life’s greatest difficulties and deepest questions.</p>

<h4 id="problem-2-youre-on-your-own">Problem 2: You’re on your own.</h4>
<p>Remember, the author does not know you, and they are not around to help you integrate all of their impressive ideas into your life. That leaves the job up to you, dear reader, to get yourself into shape! So, how will you manage it? Ask anybody whose great at what they do, and they’ll likely tell you that it can be very difficult to be your own coach.</p>

<p>How can you perform your best when you’re simultaneously looking over your own shoulder judging yourself? Inevitably, we simplify the situation by binarizing outcomes. We reckon that we either succeed or fail, and we forget that we can improve without doing it perfectly, or that sometimes a thing just doesn’t work for us. Instead of accepting these more obvious answers to our struggles, we tunnel vision on success and unintentionally undermine our own self-confidence with misplaced faith and perfectionism.</p>

<p>When you’ve fallen into this trap, it can very quickly turn into a downward spiral. You’ve got your bible, you’ve learned the gospel, and now you’re on a crusade towards perfection! Push harder! Read the book again! Do it exactly the way they wrote it! Because, if you were the kind of person who the author described (i.e., a successful person), then you should be able to do what they say and be happier for it. But… you’re not happier, so it must not be working, which means you must not be doing it right, which means you’re failing… Maybe you should buy a self-help book on self-discipline… or perhaps it was a lack of self-acceptance that led to your failure… Maybe you should buy books on both topics, just to be safe.</p>

<h4 id="problem-3-life-will-be-great-tomorrow">Problem 3: Life will be great tomorrow.</h4>
<p>The most pernicious challenge of self-help books is that it engenders a mindset of putting off one’s sense of wellbeing to an arbitrary time in the future. Once you get this time management system down, then you’ll be happy. Once you lose 30 pounds and get abs, then you’ll be happy. Once you can run a marathon, then you’ll be happy.</p>

<p>This is a problem. As anybody who has accomplished anything knows: happiness is fleeting. A first kiss lasts but a moment. You return to your seat after collecting your diploma. Eventually you drift off to sleep after the best night of your life. Wellbeing is predicated on contentment, and contentment must happen in the present moment where the content of real life actually exists. We must learn to be happy with what we already have, with who we already are. But the very concept of self-help books is that we can be better, and we should be better, and here’s a simple way to do it, and we should not compromise on our potential!</p>

<p>Consequently, too many self-help books promise more than they can deliver on. They offer grand promises of perfect productivity leading to the top of your career! An absolutely perfect training system that will lead you to smash records and be interviewed by Sports Illustrated. Of course, there’s nothing wrong with having a dream, but to pretend that a book can be a perfect road map to that dream and then conditioning one’s happiness on whether that dream is achieved is a recipe for disappointment and self-loathing. You couldn’t do it, and since you tried to do it by yourself, you have only yourself to blame, you loser.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>
<p>I don’t want to dismiss the whole project of self-improvement as invalid. However, I think we should rethink our approach to the self-help genre by individually considering the following three points:</p>

<h5 id="know-your-circumstances">Know your circumstances</h5>
<p>First, we must recognize that the authors of these books cannot know our lives in any detail, so the burden falls to us to know what may or may not work for our unique circumstances.</p>

<h5 id="set-your-own-criteria">Set your own criteria</h5>
<p>Second, all of the work in interpretation and implementation of any self-help advice falls to us, the reader. Consequently, we must set the criteria for success and failure ourselves, with all their requisite gradients, while also maintaining the knowledge that nothing works for everyone.</p>

<h5 id="no-silver-bullet">No silver bullet</h5>
<p>Finally, no book (or anything else) is a silver bullet. We will never figure everything out, and any attempt to do so will inevitably breed more problems, which then need to be figured out, and so on. As such, we must remember to find contentment with ourselves now despite our shortcomings, and still strive to improve ourselves.</p>

<h4 id="final-word">Final Word</h4>
<p>While many self-help books offer legitimate advice, many others overpromise, underdeliver, repackage common sense, or veer off into something one could only consider obliquely helpful. As long as we recognize the limits of these books and exercise our personal agency, then we can keep what’s good about self-help while avoiding its dark side.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wasted Time (Creative Fiction)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wasted-time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wasted Time (Creative Fiction)" /><published>2024-03-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-03-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wasted-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wasted-time"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="wasted-time">Wasted Time</h1>

<p>A great plume of chalky smoke enshrouded the old school bus as it shuttered to a halt on the remnants of an old gravel road. “Here we are!” the driver shouted over the sputtering engine before shifting to neutral and killing it. He twisted his skinny frame around and lifted his sunglasses to look down the corrugated runway and found the last person left onboard.</p>

<p>“Well,” he said, scratching his scruff. “Just you then huh, brother?”</p>

<p>The man looked around and then up at the driver. “Yeah, guess so,” he said.</p>

<p>“Right on,” said the driver, “you got a long day of paddlin’ ahead of you.”</p>

<p>“Yeah, guess so. It’s thirteen miles to camp, right?” he asked, already knowing the answer. He stood up and swung his pack onto his shoulder.</p>

<p>“Yep, that’s right.” The driver spun around and started jostling the dirty silver bar to open the door, and with a few curse words he managed to succeed. “Woooeeee it’s gon be a hot one today!” he hollered as he landed with a crunch on the sunbaked gravel. The man onboard slid out from between the cracked green seats and followed the driver out into the sunshine.</p>

<p>It was a beautiful summer day. The sky was a deep blue with cotton puffs of white clouds floating along at their lazy leisure. The man blinked hard and pulled the brim of his baseball cap down to shield his eyes from the brightness. Gently flowing water caressed a rocky bank a few dozen yards away, its surface danced with short lengths of glittering ribbons, a happy refusal of the copious sunshine that rained down everywhere as if the river had had its fill and could swallow no more.</p>

<p>The bus driver had walked to the metal carriage that was towed behind the bus and pulled down the last canoe which he was now dragging towards the water. He stopped in the shade of a great birch tree that sat between the bus and the river.</p>

<p>“Aight lemme give you some talk right quick, brother,” and he waved to the man to come closer.</p>

<p>“First of all, my name’s Curtis, and I’m s’posed to make sure yer gonna be safe out there on the water. Y’ever canoe before?” he asked as the man approached. “I sure hope so since yer out her by yaself.”</p>

<p>“Oh yeah I’ve done plenty. I was in the scouts when I was a boy.”</p>

<p>Curtis sniffed and then lifted his hat off to wipe his sweaty brow, revealing a balding dome at the precipice of shoulder length hair.</p>

<p>“Okay, good. I’ll just tell ya that the front desk at camp closes up at dark, so ya gotta get back down there b’fore then. If yer not back, that means I gotta come n’ find ya.” He spit on the ground. “I don’t wanna drag my ass out of camp and up the river in the dark my friend.” He paused, looked the man over, and leaned forward to look him in the eyes. ”Thirteen miles’s pretty far.”</p>

<p>“Yeah it’s no problem. I’ll be back before dark, I promise.”</p>

<p>“Okay, good,” he said, and he leaned back again. “Ya got enough water and supplies?”</p>

<p>“Yeah I’m all stocked up,” and he gestured to the back of the bus where his cooler remained.</p>

<p>“Okay then. Yer paddle and life vest’s sittin’ there in the canoe. Y’aint gotta wear the jacket, but I have to give it to ya.”</p>

<p>“Yeah, I understand. I’m not gonna need it, though.”</p>

<p>“Rock on, brother. Well, I’ll grab yer cooler for ya.”</p>

<p>“Thanks.”</p>

<p>Curtis turned with a clap of the hands and headed towards the rear of the bus. The man threw his bag into the empty canoe and walked down to the bank to let the water wash over his sandaled feet. The water was cool and clear, and he could see the bright spill of smoothed river rocks carpeting the bottom. A few small fish gathered in a pool nearby, black raindrops endlessly falling into the river flow. He closed his eyes and felt the gentle sensations of the current sweep over his feet.</p>

<p>“Alright brother!” Curtis shouted as he dropped the cooler heavily to the ground behind the canoe. The man snapped out of his reverie and walked back to the shade of the birch tree. “You be safe now, ya hear? I’ll see you back at camp ‘fore dark.” He leaned back to squint up at the sky and then looked back down at the man. He paused. “Make the most of yer day out here, brother. It’s hot out, but I’ll be damned if it ain’t a beauty.” The man nodded in agreement and flashed him a smile. “Truly.” The short silence between them swelled with the music of the southern Missouri wilderness: the low buzz of flying insects, gently trickling water, songbirds in nearby trees. Curtis returned his nod, turned, and began strutting back towards the bus.</p>

<p>“By the way, do you have the time?”</p>

<p>Curtis didn’t seem to hear his question, and soon he was pulling the door closed behind him after he had climbed the narrow staircase up to his seat. After a few labored attempts the bus’s engine kicked to life and was brought around to face back the way they had come. Curtis gave the man one last parting nod as the dirty yellow block lurched forward down the gravel drive and out of sight, leaving a smoky white haze in its wake. “Finally,” said the man, and he walked back down to the shore where he had stood in the water.</p>

<hr />

<p>It was still early, but Curtis was right, thirteen miles would take quite a while. The man wondered how much time he could spend out of his canoe for the day, but a few seconds after the mental math started he gave up the effort and decided to move at his own pace. He pulled off his sun shirt, sat in the canoe beneath the birch tree, and began rifling through his pack: a water bottle, sunglasses, a rain jacket, a waterproof bag with his phone, wallet, and keys, a first aid kit, and sunscreen. He pulled out the sunscreen and thoroughly lathered his pale skin, dolloping an extra bit along the bridge of his nose. He remembered to apply some to his feet, having learned the hard way how painful sunburns on the tops of feet could be. He balled up his sunshirt and stuffed it along with the sunscreen back into the pack. Then he dug out the water bottle and took a swig. The flowing river beckoned him into its cool embrace. It was still early, but it was already sweltering in the late July heat, and the humidity was suffocating.</p>

<p>“I better hang out for a few minutes before shoving off so I can let the sunscreen absorb,” he thought to himself, and he reclined back in the canoe using his pack as a pillow and closed his eyes. “Why rush? I’m out here to savor this.” The cicada’s loud song filled the air. He listened to their rhythmic chirping swell and abate like the rise and fall of great lungs. A fly whirled around his face and he lazily whisked it away. “Good lord I’m already so sweaty,” he thought. He packed a thermos of iced coffee in his cooler, and he smiled at the imagined moment of its first sip. He thought of all the time he spent in collared shirts staring into a computer screen with a cup of burnt coffee on his desk. That world seemed so far away and absurd out here, filled with clocks and meetings, square-edged surfaces and square-edged people. The treetops began rustling, and a gentle breeze carrying the round vegetable smell of the river water washed over him, cooling his sweaty skin, and dissolving any remaining thoughts of that far off gray office. “Ohhh yeah, that is gooood,” he whispered to himself, and he sank a little deeper into the canoe.</p>

<p>A short time later he awoke to the sound of birds chirping loudly in the branches overhead. “Guess I dozed off,” he muttered. He sprang up out of the canoe and did some jumping jacks to shake out the grogginess that weighed down his limbs. It was time to get moving. He placed the cooler in the center of the craft with his pack behind it so it would be within reach from his seat in the stern. He used the life jacket as a cushion for the metal bench, which served the dual purpose of softening the seat and preventing it from becoming molten in the sun’s relentless shine. “My ass will be soooo grateful for this,” he smirked inwardly. Lastly he slanted the paddle across the bench and slid it securely down into the nook between the cooler and the hull. With that, he dragged the bow of the vessel through the reedy bank and into the water before jumping in and setting off downriver.</p>

<hr />

<p>The sun sailed slowly towards its peak in the azure sky as he paddled along. The water wound its way through thick woodlands that occasionally broke on either side with rocky beaches and sandbars. Willow trees draped over deep pools where rafts of tiny bubbles formed from hidden fish that would swim up from the depths to snag unsuspecting insects resting on the surface. Occasionally he would encounter obstacles on the river: big rocks jutting up from the surface, an old rotted oak tree pulled down by use of a rope swing, now just frayed tatters twirling aimlessly in the current.</p>

<p>Every once in a while the canoe would grind to a halt in the shallowest parts of the river and he would step out into the water to grab the bow of the craft and drag it over the pebbles and river rocks. On one of these occasions at a particularly sunny stretch of shallow river, he looked down to see a glinting orb partly buried among the rocks between his feet. He paused, and with one hand still clutching the boat, he reached into the water, plucked the object, and lifted it close to his face for examination. It was an old pocket watch. He turned the watch over in his hands a few times and measured its weight with a few bounces of the wrist. The stem was crooked and the gold-plated case had scratches all over it, but it shone brilliantly golden in the sun. On the back there was an engraving in elegant script that was mostly worn away. All he could make out was what looked to be two words: wasted time. He blinked, and then scrutinized the inscription for a few more moments. “Hm,” he grunted. He released the clasp and popped open the cover to reveal smashed glass, waterlogged and dirt ridden. The spiderweb fractures obscured the face completely, and he couldn’t tell what time the watch had stopped or even whether the hands remained inside at all. A smile slowly crept across his face, and he felt a sense of joy for his good fortune at finding such an interesting thing in the river. He cradled the watch in his fingers for a moment before flicking the cover closed and slipping it into his pocket. Then he continued his scraping march through the shallows.</p>

<p>A short time later he ran the canoe aground on a large sandy bank that had ample shade and a few overturned logs: a perfect place to stop for lunch. He dragged the vessel up onto the beach and then moved his cooler and pack over into a shady depression with a nice smooth log to sit on. He ate a turkey sandwich for lunch with some tortilla chips and an apple. He washed down the lunch with a long swig from a sweaty bottle of gatorade that still held a trace of coolness from his refrigerator where he took it from that morning. Finally, he took out the thermos of iced coffee, and as he enjoyed the longed-for sip he had imagined that morning he retrieved the pocket watch from his pocket and turned it over in his hand several times, impressed with the strange artifact. He studied the inscription more carefully this time, but all he could make out were the same words as before: wasted time.</p>

<p>The heat was blistering as sweat from his brow dripped down his nose and onto the watch he held in his hands. He wiped his forehead and slipped the watch back into his pocket. He was happy to be out of the craft and in the shade. How far had he come? Maybe five miles or so? Regardless of the exact answer, he had a long way to go, and it was time to press on. He had yet to see anybody else on the river today, and he hoped that it would stay that way.</p>

<hr />

<p>A couple hours later he came by a couple enjoying a picnic on a sandbar. They had spread an old gingham blanket over a patch of shady sand and had a small speaker playing some generic country music. The large man laid like a beached walrus sprawled out on his back with his round hairy stomach glistening in the heat, a fishing hat pulled down to cover his face. A tall beer can rested between his arm and torso. The woman with him was only slightly less large than he was. She was propped up on an elbow next to him with half a cigarette burning between her lips. She was scrolling through her phone when she noticed the man on the river.</p>

<p>“Hiiiii!” she cried out to him in a high, sweet voice. Her companion did not stir.</p>

<p>The man in the canoe returned her wave and gave her a big smile, hoping that she wouldn’t try to strike up a conversation. She stuck the cigarette’s lit end into the sand, heaved herself up, and then walked barefoot to the water’s edge.</p>

<p>“Aren’t choo hot out there?” she asked as he floated closer. He dipped the oar to the starboard side and ran the canoe into the sand, his midwestern sensibilities preventing him from being even a little rude to a stranger.</p>

<p>“Yeah, it’s hot, but I’m doin’ okay,” he said with a smile.</p>

<p>“Where’d you get in?”</p>

<p>“Hmm. Not sure exactly. Maybe seven or eight miles back?”</p>

<p>“Ooohhh,” she squealed, “so you’re doin’ the whole thing, huh?”</p>

<p>“Guess so. I just did the longest float that they offered.”</p>

<p>“Oh, you’re with that camp down there then?”</p>

<p>“Yeah.”</p>

<p>“So not the whole thing,” she said, a little disappointment in her voice.</p>

<p>“Guess not,” he paused.</p>

<p>A short silence passed between them before she spoke again. “Where are my manners? My name is Betty and that man over there is my husband, Alex.” She glanced back towards the sleeping man. “Alex over there, he loves this river. He and his friends floated the whole thing a bunch of times. They’ve done it on kayaks, on rafts, on canoes, and one time they even did it with just some floaties on their arms! They put the beer cooler in its own tube that time, too,” she said with a laugh. “I used to worry ‘bout his antics, but I just pray to the lord and he always comes back to me okay.”</p>

<p>“Wow, that’s great,” and he paid her a smile.</p>

<p>“He works so hard these days though,” she said, her tone falling. “Work ain’t easy to come by round here. Nowadays when we come down to the water we like to just lay around and rest. Usually we bring the dogs and the kids, but it’s nice to have some privacy just for the two of us this time. It can be pretty romantic by the water, don’t ya think?”</p>

<p>“Yeah, I guess so,” replied the man, and he looked over at the sleeping man.</p>

<p>“You out here by yourself, hon?” she asked.</p>

<p>“Oh yeah, I enjoy the solitude out here.”</p>

<p>“Well maybe next time you can bring a girlfriend, if you have one that is.”</p>

<p>“Yeah, maybe,” he replied, a little annoyed. “By the way, do you have the time?”</p>

<p>Betty scrunched her face and held a stubby finger to her chin. “Hmm, I’m not too sure. Reckon it’s round three thirty now. Maybe four. Alex finished his shift at three and we came down here not too long after. Could be four thirty. Maybe even five. I can get my phone and check if ya want.”</p>

<p>“Nah that’s okay, it doesn’t really matter,” he paused. “I better keep moving, though.” He stuck the oar into the bank to push himself back into the water. “It was nice meeting you, Betty. Hope you two enjoy the evening,” he said, and he meant it. With a strong push the bow released from the bank and he righted the vessel to face downstream where it could resume its ride on the current.</p>

<p>“Okay, hon, you be safe out there now,” she sang, eyes squinting with a big toothy smile. She turned and walked back to her motionless husband. She knelt behind him and emerged with another cigarette which she lipped and lit in one fluid motion. Then she layed back down on her elbow and resumed scrolling her phone exactly as she had been before.</p>

<hr />

<p>Sweat dripped from the curls of the man’s hair onto his pink shoulders and thighs as he paddled the canoe in the late afternoon sun. Sometimes he would reach into the river and splash water onto himself to drench and cool his body for a few moments before the sun’s angry rays evaporated the relief. The sun had begun its descent past its precipice, but the heat was still punishing. The surface of the water was spotted with patches of leafy shade from the canopy of trees that hugged the western banks, so the man steered his craft into these shady spots as much as he could, seeking any reprieve he could find.</p>

<p>His life back home felt very far away out here, and he began to think of it as a strange, almost alien lifestyle. His days started with a digital song blared out from a little glass rectangle on a plastic table beside his bed. He’d drag himself out of the warm, synthetic cocoon of sheets and into the bathroom where water of all temperatures would shoot out of metal tubes hidden behind walls made of a mysterious chalky substance. Breakfast was made of food he’d bought at a big store around the corner, shipped in boxes from unknown places. He’d get into a metal, wheeled box and drive to a big, box-shaped building, the inside of which was subdivided into further boxes of various sizes, the bigger ones reserved for those who had shown the most skill at navigating this box-world. Then he’d sit in his personal work box, stare into an electrified panel, and he would think very carefully about the special selection of conceptual boxes he was paid to think about. Each night, he’d return home by the same means he used to leave it, and he’d choose one of several electrified panels (this time for entertainment) to stare at until it was time to crawl back into bed.</p>

<p>He knew he was being unfair to his life back home. His job served a purpose, and he was good at it. Plus, he liked his life most days. He tried to balance out the dark picture he had painted in his head with a few brighter strokes, but to no avail. The more he thought about his life back home the more absurd it seemed to him, and it began to seem like his day-to-day life kept him more complacent than satisfied. He began to wonder what sort of lifestyle Curtis the bus driver led out here working on a little river in rural Missouri. He couldn’t be earning very much money, and there was no way the camp was employing him beyond the summer months. Maybe he had a second job, or maybe he moved around between the seasons.</p>

<p>Just then, the man was captured by a glimpse of himself driving an old bus down a gravel road; he was poorly shaven, his hair was long and unkempt, and he had a little smirking grin on his face, as if he had just gotten away with cheating on an unfairly difficult math test. He worked along the river all day, and the next morning he drove his truck back to his little place tucked at the end of a long dirt driveway in the woods. It wasn’t big, but big enough to be comfortable for himself and maybe another should that day ever come. He opened the door, greeted his dog, and walked to the fridge to crack open a cold one. Then he’d decide what to do next. Maybe he’d go sit on the porch with a book or guitar and he’d waste the day away. Maybe he’d head into town and play pool with some buddies. Whatever he’d decide to do, no clock would be making the decision for him.</p>

<p>The canoe suddenly ground to a halt, shaking him out of his reverie. He was back on the river, run aground on another stretch of shallows. The music of nature returned to his ears: the running water, the rustling of treetops, and the humming sound of insects punctuated by the chirping of birds. He exhaled and closed his eyes; then he reached into his pocket and held the pocket watch. He sat in silence for some time as the river parted and curled around the sleek body of the canoe beneath him. Finally, after a few minutes, he opened his eyes, stepped out of the canoe, and began dragging it along through the shallows.</p>

<hr />

<p>The sky had turned to an ombre of pink and pale blue as the sun fell towards the horizon in the western sky. The heat had finally abated and the man in the canoe had pulled his sun shirt back over his body to shield himself from the hordes of mosquitoes that had come out with the cooling temperatures. Though plenty of time remained before darkness, the water had turned opaque and the bottom could no longer be seen through the thick maple depths.</p>

<p>“I’ve gotta be getting close now,” he thought to himself. Beneath his sunshirt was a lather of sweat, sunscreen, and sand, which irritated his sunburned shoulders. The muscles in his arms and back were tired from paddling all day, and the chafing in his swim trunks was getting hot. He was already fantasizing about the shower and clean change of clothes waiting for him back at camp, but first, he had to get out of this canoe.</p>

<p>As he came around a sharp bend in the river he was greeted suddenly by the full force of the setting sun. He pulled the brim of his hat down to shield his eyes as the violent echo of the incandescent gaze remained stubbornly in the center of his vision. The disco surface of the water was inscrutable as the neon ribbons of watery sunshine danced everywhere. He dipped the oar starboard to bring the canoe into a nearby bank when he felt the bow strike and catch something firm. The stern whipped around its new fulcrum and hammered into a jutting stump, capsizing and spilling its innards into the flow. The man surfaced a short time later, violently coughing water out of his lungs.</p>

<p>He scrambled to pull his cooler and backpack to the nearby bank, coughing all the while, and he thanked himself for buying the waterproof bag to protect his phone. The oar had gotten stuck in a tangle of driftwood a few yards from the wreck, and he trudged into the water to wrestle it. With a lot of effort he dragged the mostly-submerged canoe ashore and tipped it over to return its contents back to the river. He looked around for the life jacket, but couldn’t find it, and after a while he gave it up and accepted that he’d owe the camp a few extra dollars. It was an unfortunate consequence of his unfortunate mistake.</p>

<p>Having rescued what he could from the wreck he sat down in the empty canoe and let out a small laugh. How close he had come to a whole day on the river without tipping! He peeled the shirt off his body, wrung it out over the rocks, and then put it back on again before any mosquitoes could find his exposed skin. Leaning back into a patch of tall grass he tilted his chin up and let out a long sigh, releasing the last of the stress he had just undergone. “No time to rest now,” he muttered to himself. He thought of Curtis waiting back at camp counting down the minutes before he had to go look for some city boy out in the dark. He rather liked Curtis, and he didn’t want to cause him any trouble. Plus, his pride was on the line. He said he could do the full thirteen miles before dark, and god dammit he would do it. He rose and started to repack the canoe when he heard a faint whooshing sound in the distance. Then another.</p>

<p>“That must be the highway,” he said aloud. “I’m close.”</p>

<p>Reinvigorated, he doubled his efforts to get back on the water. He plopped the cooler and backpack to their positions and flung the oar across the now naked stern bench. He dragged the vessel back to the water and hopped in. With a few powerful strokes he was back in the current with speed.</p>

<hr />

<p>A narrow beach emerged from behind a stand of trees as he rounded the final bend of his journey. He greeted the site with a broad smile and then drove the canoe like a nail into the shoreline. The beach was flanked by a mossy embankment made of old stones dragged out of the riverbed. Above it the old school bus sat waiting patiently like a dog for its master, its carriage full of overturned kayaks and canoes dripping in the twilight.  His arms stretched towards the sky, and with a satisfied grunt, he stepped out of the craft for the last time and began dragging it up the beach. The temperature had dropped with the sun as it descended behind the westerly treeline and across the campground he could see flickering campfires, some partly hidden behind lumpy silhouettes.</p>

<p>A shadowy figure approached from the lawn above the embankment as the man lifted his possessions from the boat to a nearby picnic table.</p>

<p>“Well well the progidal son returns!” said Curtis, unaware that he said prodigal wrong. “I was keepin’ an eye out for ya, brother. Ya got back just in time, s’gonna be dark soon.” He grabbed the bow of the empty canoe and dragged it towards the carriage.</p>

<p>“Mind givin’ me a hand here?” Curtis asked.</p>

<p>“Sure,” replied the man. They carried the canoe behind the bus and hoisted it up onto the metal bars of the carriage. Then they clapped the sand from their hands and strolled back towards the picnic table.</p>

<p>“So what? Ya have a good time out there?”</p>

<p>“Oh yeah, a great time. Hey, check this out. Look what I found on the river,” and he reached into his empty pocket. Frantically, he reached into his other pocket, only to discover that the pocket watch was gone.</p>

<p>“Oh shit! Damn, it must have… I guess it… it must have slipped out of my pocket when I flipped.”</p>

<p>“Haha you flipped, eh?” Curtis teased and then leaned over to slap his knee.</p>

<p>“Yeah I flipped just up there. But further upriver I found this broken watch in the water. It was old and had some inscription on it, but now… damn. Can’t believe I lost it…”, he said, shaking his head. “Oh, by the way, I think I owe you guys a life vest.”</p>

<p>“No shit, really?” some new gravity in Curtis’ voice that the man did not expect.</p>

<p>“Uh, yeah, I lost the vest when I flipped. What is that like thirty bucks? I’ll pay for it, I don’t mind.”</p>

<p>“Nah man, I mean the watch.” He took a step closer. “Was it a gold pocket watch?”</p>

<p>The two men locked eyes.</p>

<p>“Yeah… wait, was that… your watch?” he asked.</p>

<p>Curtis took another step closer, looked to his left and right, and then dropped his voice. “Nah man, I found that same watch on the river last summer and lost it ‘fore I got back to camp, same as you.” He touched his nose. “Did it say somethin ‘bout… wasted time?”</p>

<p>“Yeah, yeah it did,” the man replied, nearly whispering.</p>

<p>“Thought so… Wanna know the craziest thing?”</p>

<p>The man gave a short nod, eyes fixated and wide.</p>

<p>“I met another guy who found that very same watch the year b‘fore I did, and he lost it, too. Just like we did! And he says that some guy before him found it and lost it, too!”</p>

<p>The man let out a short laugh. “You’re fuckin’ with me,” he said with a smirk.</p>

<p>Curtis stood up tall and puffed out his chest. “Brother. I ain’t fuckin’ with shit. I ain’t about them superstitions, man. This is different. That watch keeps showin’ up, like some kinda sign. This is some right strangeness. Believe me man, believe it or not. I ain’t lyin’.”</p>

<p>“Hmm.” The man was so certain he was being played that he hadn’t at all expected Curtis to be sincere. He was skeptical that they had found the same watch, but it wasn’t impossible, and Curtis did know about the inscription, which was a bit beyond coincidence. ”Well, whatever it is, it sure is strange…,” he admitted. He glanced back at the water and then returned his gaze to meet Curtis’. “Well, if it is a sign, what do you think it means? Is it good luck or something? Bad luck maybe?”</p>

<p>“I don’t know, man,” Curtis said as he stroked his chin. “Reckon my luck’s been ‘bout the same since I came upon it. What do you think it means?”</p>

<p>The man thought for a moment.</p>

<p>“I don’t know. Guess it could mean anything.”</p>

<p>For a brief moment they stood together in a silence that swelled with the sounds of the newfallen night. Frogs croaked, owls hooted, and the hum of insects droned along in crooked harmony. A gentle breeze came off the darkened river.</p>

<p>“By the way, do you have the time?”</p>

<p>“Nah, brother,” Curtis sighed. He leaned back to look up at the stars emerging in the twilight, “I just rise and fall with the sun.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning" /><published>2022-12-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="grounded-cognition-and-reinforcement-learning">Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning</h1>

<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>

<p>Grounded cognition as we know it today was born out of a reaction against the early to middle 20th century psychological view of cognition as an amodal system of symbolic representation and manipulation. However, grounded cognition has in fact been the dominant view of cognition for most of recorded history and extends back to ancient philosophers like Epicurus (Barsalou, 1999, J. Prinz 2002, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). From the perspective of grounded cognition, it is unlikely that the brain contains amodal symbols. Further, if it does happen to contain amodal symbols, they must work together with modal representations to create cognition (Barsalou, 2008). Instead, the grounded perspective stresses an emphasis on the interactions between perception, action, the body, the environment, and other agents, typically during goal achievement. The mechanisms by which cognition operates within these interactions include simulation, situated action, and bodily states. The emphasis on agent, environment, goal achievement, and situated action positions grounded cognition as particularly suitable to modeling using reinforcement learning, a computational approach focused on goal-directed learning through interaction (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). Indeed, grounded cognition and reinforcement learning are a natural pairing, with evidence from the former being largely accounted for by the theoretical outlook of the latter. In what follows we describe reinforcement learning, discuss theories of grounded cognition in that context, and then step through evidence presented in Barsalou’s Grounded Cognition (Barsalou, 2008).</p>

<h4 id="reinforcement-learning">Reinforcement Learning</h4>

<p>Reinforcement learning (RL) is a computational approach to learning from interaction, and is commonly used in machine learning and robotics (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). In a nutshell, RL is learning what to do so as to maximize a reward signal. It is characterized by two distinguishing properties: trial-and-error search, and delayed reward. That is, the agent does not know what actions to take in advance but must discover them by trial and error, and similarly, the agent does not know how rewarding its actions will be or how rewards may aggregate over time. Thus, it must consider the known and unknown, as well as delayed and immediate rewards.</p>

<p>The conflict between immediate and delayed rewards presents a primary challenge for RL: the tradeoff between exploration and exploitation. How can an agent balance between behaviors it knows are rewarding versus exploring for new behaviors that may be potentially more (or less) rewarding? This exploitation-exploration tradeoff is another key feature of RL. The following components constitute an RL model: a policy, a reward function, a value function, and (optionally) a model of the environment (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). An agent’s policy maps perceived states of the environment to actions that can be taken in those states and psychologically corresponds to a set of stimulus-response rules. Its reward function maps each perceived state-action pair to a reward (immediate rewards). Its value function represents the total amount of reward an agent can expect to accumulate over the future from its current state (long-term rewards). An agent uses its model of the environment (model) and bodily state to determine a set of potential actions to take (policy). It then chooses an action to take based on consideration of both immediate (reward function) and long-term (value function) rewards.</p>

<p>What makes RL unique to other computational learning approaches is that it characterizes a learning problem rather than a method (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). This shift in focus inherently encapsulates an agent, its motivation, and its environment, making it amenable to the grounded view of cognition.</p>

<h4 id="grounded-cognition">Grounded Cognition</h4>

<p>There are several theories of grounded cognition, each capturing different aspects of how humans operate within the world. Each theory builds off the importance of simulation, situated action, and bodily states.</p>

<p>First, we consider cognitive linguistics theories, which assert that people possess extensive knowledge of their bodies and experiences. Abstract concepts draw upon this knowledge metaphorically. To demonstrate, consider the ubiquitous use of concrete metaphors to discuss abstract concepts across cultures (e.g., happiness is associated with “up” and sadness with “down”) (Lakoff &amp; Johnson, 1980, 1999, as cited in Barsalou, 2008).</p>

<p>Second, there are theories of situated action, which focus on the central roles of perception and action in cognition. These theories place emphasis on the tight coupling of environment, goal achievement, and social interaction, which engender a focus on dynamic systems rather than computational architectures that only manipulate symbols.</p>

<p>Both classes of theories align with RL, where learning and behavior is undertaken by a goal-directed agent within an environment. Note that the agents we are concerned with are humans who operate as social creatures within a social environment and consequently have social goals. A final class of theories are those of cognitive simulation, which can be subdivided into perceptual symbol systems, memory theories, and social simulation theories. Perceptual symbol systems integrate traditional symbolic systems with grounded cognition via simulation of symbol manipulation (i.e., you can internally imagine and manipulate symbols to which you have previously been exposed). Grounded memory theories originated out of the belief that past theories of memory have focused too much on passive storage and not enough on situated action. Glenberg proposed that memory primarily serves to control situated action, and that stored memories reflect bodily actions and their ability to mesh with goal pursuit (Glenberg, 1997, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Social simulation theories offer a grounded view of interpersonal interaction. It is argued that theory of mind – where one infers another’s internal state – is achieved through the representation of another’s mind by simulating one’s own. Relatedly, mirror neurons are an interesting component of social cognition, as they fire when we perceive an action taken by another person. Importantly, mirror neurons respond to the goal of the action, not the action itself, which echoes the RL focus on goal-directed learning and behavior.</p>

<p>Indeed, all these cognitive simulation theories can be represented in the RL framework as an agent’s policy and reward/value function, where the agent simulates the potential actions available to it and assigns rewards to those actions prior to choosing one. Further, if we take Glenberg’s view of stored memories as primarily to control situated action, then we can consider the memories of the agent to be the learning resulting from the RL process. As actions are taken, memory (policy) is updated to reflect its outcome (reward function/ value function). From a theoretical view, this is a nice start on mapping grounded cognition to RL, but how does this mapping hold up with empirical findings?</p>

<h4 id="relation-to-empirical-findings">Relation to Empirical Findings</h4>

<p>There has been much work showing how simulation, situations, and bodily states play central roles in cognition. In the domain of perception and action, results show that perception of the world influences which actions are perceived to be available, and, conversely, the actions perceive as available influence how the world is perceived. States of perception get stored in memory, and are later triggered when similar stimuli are presented, which produces perceptual inferences that go beyond what is perceived, a useful mechanism for determining how best to act in a familiar situation (Goldstone, 1995; Hanson, 2006 as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Relatedly, as visual objects are perceived, simulations of potential actions become active in preparation for situated action. Indeed, even perception of space is shaped by how the body may act within it (Franklin &amp; Tversky, 1990, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). The intertwined relationship between perception and action reflects the stimulus-response pairs available to an agent. Note that perception here includes internal states (i.e., perception includes simulation). In the RL framework, the policy reflects an agent’s current state (perception) and its potential choices (actions). In the grounded view, one’s policy would be under continuous revision as the world and new behavior is explored. However, one’s attention would align accordingly with the policy most suitable to the situation, thereby biasing perception towards the elements relevant to that policy. This accounts for the perceptual distortion within the perception-action (stimulus-response) cycle.</p>

<p>With respect to memory, both implicit and explicit memory have been shown to heavily rely on multimodal simulations of previous episodes (Roediger &amp; McDermott, 1993; Schacter et al., 2004; Paivio, 1971, 1986; Conway, 1990, 2002; Rubin, 2006, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Simulations of stimuli held in implicit memory improve perceptual fluency and increase the likelihood of correct categorization of subsequent stimuli. Simulation within explicit memory appears central to constructing future events from past events. Working memory has been shown to be maintained by simulations of absent stimuli. Further, when stimuli is relevant to visual imagery, the motor system becomes engaged, suggesting that the salience of the simulation is related to how our bodies may use it to act (Barsalou, 2008). We can map the grounded view of memory onto the RL concept of policy (again), where an agent uses past experiences as a mapping between perception and action. By simulating past experiences (implicitly or explicitly) we bias our attention to what we believe will be important to achieve our goals (implicit or explicit) given our current state. Successfully doing so results in improved performance, whereas unsuccessful attention may result in surprise and subsequently a larger policy (memory/belief) update.</p>

<p>While simulation in memory has been accepted for many years, simulation as the basis of knowledge representation is still considered a radical proposal (Barsalou, 2008). However, even here there is evidence for the grounded view of cognition. There has been work demonstrating that properties are more difficult to describe as they become larger, and that many detailed properties are difficult to verbalize. Both findings indirectly support the idea that we simulate objects and their properties to verify them (Solomon &amp; Barsalou, 2004; Morison &amp; Tversky, 1997, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Additionally, lesion damage to different parts of the brain results in the loss of conceptual categories. For example, damage to the visual cortex results in the loss of the animal categories, as we categorize animals by their visual properties. Similarly, damage to the motor cortex results in the loss of tools, as we categorize tools by how we use them with our bodies. Everything we know about the world is stored in our brains, and the RL mechanism by which knowledge is updated is through exploration and exploitation, action and reward, and the environmental state and goal-pursuit. It stands to reason that the knowledge we learn is tightly coupled within the context in which it was learned, which includes how we came to learn it, including the brain regions involved in our learning. However, this connection is somewhat tenuous, as RL intentionally avoids the concept of knowledge on its own and is instead focused on the learning problem as a whole. One might make the argument that knowledge is encapsulated within the notion of policy, but it is not explicit. Indeed, one of the reasons RL seems to be so successful is that it does not attempt to nail down what knowledge is, but rather how an agent learns in an environment to achieve a goal.</p>

<h4 id="simulation">Simulation</h4>

<p>In what has been discussed, we can notice a pattern emerging. Simulation is the mechanism in grounded cognition by which agents make sense and act within world, which consists of a body and environment. Further, perception of the world is contingent on the simulations maintained by the agent and is often biased towards available action choices. This relationship between state and action is well captured by the notion of policy within RL. As we consider other findings found in grounded cognition, we find again and again the suitability of RL to explain them. Take the domain of language comprehension. The meaning of language is simulated using situation models, which represent information with spatial properties (Barsalou, 2008). In other words, readers comprehend text by simulating what they read. Findings show that reading an action word activates the motor system. Similarly, readers simulate affect (emotional states) during comprehension. If we take the goal of reading to be comprehension, then comprehension can be thought of as the successful recall and integration of the meanings of the words. To that extent, RL is perfectly suitable to explain language comprehension (although the process itself would happen very rapidly). The policy (stimulus-response) would consist of rapid choices (likely unconsciously made) of integrating the meaning of language into one’s internal representation (or situation model). The reward function would be the immediate comprehensibility of one’s internal representation after integration of the most recent language, and the value function would be represented as the cohesiveness of the meaning of the overall thrust of the complete message communicated. The flexibility of RL can be used to extend to all sorts of phenomena in grounded cognition. In the domain of thought, physical reasoning relies on simulations of physical situations, suggesting that past experiences inform the understanding and reasoning of the current physical world (i.e., the policy has updated to inform current state-action choices). Mental model theory is used to explain abstract reasoning, and there is evidence that simulation plays a key role. Additionally, social cognition relies on simulation (that’s what empathy is!). In each case (language comprehension, thought, and social cognition), the problem can be broken down and represented as an RL model. The policy consists of choice-action pairs based on past experiences and the current environment, while the goal is defined as successful comprehension, or reasoning, or social connection, and the reward reflects the success of the interpretation, thinking, or communicating towards achieving its respective goal.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>Reinforcement learning is well-suited to explain the theories and evidence prominent in grounded cognition, but there are still some gaps to address. First, as mentioned earlier, there is no explicit definition of what knowledge is within RL. In my view, this is no problem, as knowledge is captured within the notion of policy (in a functional sense). However, it may be desirable to extend a version of RL to make a concrete definition of knowledge. Another gap to address would be the disconnect between the sequential processing of RL and the inherently dynamic, parallel, noisy processes of the grounded view of cognition, where environment and agent mutually interact with and influence each other in multiple and simultaneous ways. Perhaps the solution here is not to modify RL, but to parallelize it! Cognition is composed of myriad parallel processes, and if they can each be accounted for by an RL framework, perhaps extending the range and number of RL algorithms is the way forward. Finally, as a direction for further investigation, it would be interesting to see how the explore-exploit tradeoff is accounted for from the grounded perspective. In (Daw et al., 2006), a majority of gamblers explored new slot machines to play. How would this result hold up for decisions that have higher stakes, like choosing a spouse, trekking through unknown territory, or playing high-stakes poker? Grounded cognition and RL may offer the means to explore these problems.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<p>Barsalou, L. W. (2008). Grounded cognition. Annual Review of Psychology, 59, 617–645. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.59.103006.093639</p>

<p>Daw, N. D., O’Doherty, J. P., Dayan, P., Seymour, B., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2006). Cortical substrates for exploratory decisions in humans. Nature, 441(7095), 876–879. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04766</p>

<p>Sutton, R. S., &amp; Barto, A. G. (1998). Reinforcement Learning Chap 2. MIT Press, 465(1), 90–94. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20351022</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>