<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-10T09:06:38-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nick Hunkins</title><subtitle>Nick Hunkins&apos; personal website - Powered by Jekyll and GitHub Pages</subtitle><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><entry><title type="html">Reflection On Just Starting Out</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection On Just Starting Out" /><published>2024-04-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/just-starting-out"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="reflection-on-just-starting-out">Reflection On Just Starting Out</h1>

<h4 id="the-return-home">The Return Home</h4>

<p>I remember stepping off the jetway into Lambert Airport in St. Louis, MO. The feeling was surreal. It was March of 2017 and I had just spent the last 13 months teaching English in South Korea.</p>

<p>The feeling of coming back home was a complicated one, a swirling mixture of sadness for the end of an amazing journey and excitement for the beginning of a new one. Soon I would see my family members who had been mere faces on a screen for the past year. Soon I would see my friends and learn about what they had been up to since I’d been gone. Soon I would be broke.</p>

<p>While Korea was a life-changing experience, it certainly was not a profitable one. I had a few thousand dollars saved. It was enough to last me four months if I stretched, but I needed more. I needed a job.</p>

<h4 id="launchcode">LaunchCode</h4>

<p>Luckily for me I had wisely chosen to study math and computer science in college, so I actually had a foundation of technical skills that could be cultivated to start a career. Plus, while I had been overseas I started to read about this new thing called “Data Science.” I wasn’t really sure what it meant exactly (I still wonder sometimes), but I knew it involved working with math, machine learning, and computers. Naturally, I was intrigued, so I began studying a little bit each day before going to work.</p>

<p>When I came back home I learned about a non-profit organization called <a href="https://www.launchcode.org/">LaunchCode</a> through a friend of mine. Their mission was to get people working in tech based on their skills rather than their degrees. I put together a couple of sample projects to show what I could do and applied to their program. I was overjoyed when they accepted my application. Eventually they offered to place me in a 90-day internship in a new data science team at Graybar Electric, and I happily accepted!</p>

<h4 id="graybar">Graybar</h4>

<p>Those first few months at Graybar were spent cutting my teeth on code and collaboration. What I learned most during that time was just how different industry work operated compared to academic work. There weren’t any classes or grades or clubs. There was just our team and the projects that the team needed to get done.</p>

<p>I loved collaborating with others on difficult problems, and I could tell that I was learning quickly. I was lucky to find myself among a young and scrappy team, made up of other people like me who wanted to learn and prove they could do this kind of work well. It was composed of misfits who had tried their hand in some other discipline before pivoting into the exciting new field of data science, and at the head of this motley crew was my boss, Jeremy Salazar, who was the scrappiest of us all.</p>

<p>I truly enjoyed those first months working at Graybar, and I guess I proved something to them, because they offered me a job at the end of the internship. Less than 6 months after coming home, I had started a career in data science.</p>

<h4 id="gratitude">Gratitude</h4>

<p>As I write about this time in my life, I’m overcome with a sense of gratitude for having gotten the chances that have gotten me to where I am today. I was the beneficiary of the opportunities presented by Korea, LaunchCode, and Graybar, and I will always be grateful for having received them. After working at Graybar for a few years, another opportunity presented itself. I moved to Boulder, CO to begin a graduate education in Computer Science, but that’s for another post.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help" /><published>2024-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/unhelpful-self-help"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="the-less-helpful-side-of-self-help">The Less Helpful Side of Self-Help</h1>

<h4 id="avoiding-the-self-help-trap">Avoiding the Self-help Trap</h4>

<p>Self-help is a popular genre for a reason. Nobody knows you better than yourself, so you require some help, why not take ownership over that process? This sounds great on its surface, but there is a pernicious side-effect to this project.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong. Good things can come out of good self-help books. I’m grateful for having spent the time and energy to learn from books like Atomic Habits, Time Management for Mortals, and Deep Work, just to name a few. Smart people have smart ideas, who would have thought? In addition to the ideas themselves, reading self-help books can be deeply inspirational! You can have a better life, and here’s a new way to do it! Isn’t it wonderful to imagine? But, as is so often the case, there’s a dark side to this hopeful venture.</p>

<h4 id="problem-1-who-are-you">Problem 1: Who are you?</h4>
<p>Imagine that you’ve just purchased a self-help book at your local bookstore. Before you’ve even flipped open the cover, you’ve already made an implicit assumption: I need help, and this book has answers. With your purchase you have assumed a vulnerable mental stance and allotted the author a certain amount of trust.</p>

<p>This is a mistake. By design the book is written for a general audience – a general recipe for the average reader of the rough demographic the book was meant to target in its inception. The text may speak with authority, but its target audience is a caricature where you are a fully-fleshed human being.</p>

<p>The common strategy these books deploy is to simplify problems and then assert their correctness. In other words, they approach their reader with bravado and conveniently ignore the complexities of individual circumstances, the very complexities that give rise to life’s greatest difficulties and deepest questions.</p>

<h4 id="problem-2-youre-on-your-own">Problem 2: You’re on your own.</h4>
<p>Remember, the author does not know you, and they are not around to help you integrate all of their impressive ideas into your life. That leaves the job up to you, dear reader, to get yourself into shape! So, how will you manage it? Ask anybody whose great at what they do, and they’ll likely tell you that it can be very difficult to be your own coach.</p>

<p>How can you perform your best when you’re simultaneously looking over your own shoulder judging yourself? Inevitably, we simplify the situation by binarizing outcomes. We reckon that we either succeed or fail, and we forget that we can improve without doing it perfectly, or that sometimes a thing just doesn’t work for us. Instead of accepting these more obvious answers to our struggles, we tunnel vision on success and unintentionally undermine our own self-confidence with misplaced faith and perfectionism.</p>

<p>When you’ve fallen into this trap, it can very quickly turn into a downward spiral. You’ve got your bible, you’ve learned the gospel, and now you’re on a crusade towards perfection! Push harder! Read the book again! Do it exactly the way they wrote it! Because, if you were the kind of person who the author described (i.e., a successful person), then you should be able to do what they say and be happier for it. But… you’re not happier, so it must not be working, which means you must not be doing it right, which means you’re failing… Maybe you should buy a self-help book on self-discipline… or perhaps it was a lack of self-acceptance that led to your failure… Maybe you should buy books on both topics, just to be safe.</p>

<h4 id="problem-3-life-will-be-great-tomorrow">Problem 3: Life will be great tomorrow.</h4>
<p>The most pernicious challenge of self-help books is that it engenders a mindset of putting off one’s sense of wellbeing to an arbitrary time in the future. Once you get this time management system down, then you’ll be happy. Once you lose 30 pounds and get abs, then you’ll be happy. Once you can run a marathon, then you’ll be happy.</p>

<p>This is a problem. As anybody who has accomplished anything knows: happiness is fleeting. A first kiss lasts but a moment. You return to your seat after collecting your diploma. Eventually you drift off to sleep after the best night of your life. Wellbeing is predicated on contentment, and contentment must happen in the present moment where the content of real life actually exists. We must learn to be happy with what we already have, with who we already are. But the very concept of self-help books is that we can be better, and we should be better, and here’s a simple way to do it, and we should not compromise on our potential!</p>

<p>Consequently, too many self-help books promise more than they can deliver on. They offer grand promises of perfect productivity leading to the top of your career! An absolutely perfect training system that will lead you to smash records and be interviewed by Sports Illustrated. Of course, there’s nothing wrong with having a dream, but to pretend that a book can be a perfect road map to that dream and then conditioning one’s happiness on whether that dream is achieved is a recipe for disappointment and self-loathing. You couldn’t do it, and since you tried to do it by yourself, you have only yourself to blame, you loser.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>
<p>I don’t want to dismiss the whole project of self-improvement as invalid. However, I think we should rethink our approach to the self-help genre by individually considering the following three points:</p>

<h5 id="know-your-circumstances">Know your circumstances</h5>
<p>First, we must recognize that the authors of these books cannot know our lives in any detail, so the burden falls to us to know what may or may not work for our unique circumstances.</p>

<h5 id="set-your-own-criteria">Set your own criteria</h5>
<p>Second, all of the work in interpretation and implementation of any self-help advice falls to us, the reader. Consequently, we must set the criteria for success and failure ourselves, with all their requisite gradients, while also maintaining the knowledge that nothing works for everyone.</p>

<h5 id="no-silver-bullet">No silver bullet</h5>
<p>Finally, no book (or anything else) is a silver bullet. We will never figure everything out, and any attempt to do so will inevitably breed more problems, which then need to be figured out, and so on. As such, we must remember to find contentment with ourselves now despite our shortcomings, and still strive to improve ourselves.</p>

<h4 id="final-word">Final Word</h4>
<p>While many self-help books offer legitimate advice, many others overpromise, underdeliver, repackage common sense, or veer off into something one could only consider obliquely helpful. As long as we recognize the limits of these books and exercise our personal agency, then we can keep what’s good about self-help while avoiding its dark side.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Merits of Walking Really, Really Far</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Merits of Walking Really, Really Far" /><published>2024-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/walking-really-far"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="on-the-merits-of-walking-really-really-far">On the Merits of <br />Walking Really, Really Far</h1>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<i>Walking, ideally, is a state in which the mind, the body, and the world are aligned, as though they were three characters finally in conversation together, three notes suddenly making a chord. Walking allows us to be in our bodies and in the world without being made busy by them.</i>”</p>
  <blockquote>
    <blockquote>
      <p>Rebecca Solnit, <i>Wanderlust: A History of Walking</i></p>
    </blockquote>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="rhododenron-or">Rhododenron, OR</h4>

<p>It was a warm and sunny September day in Rhododendron, Oregon when Adam and Kylie pulled their rented Subaru into a dusty gravel parking lot. They woke in the dark of the early morning to catch a plane from Denver to Portland, and the interim 45 miles of highway from Portland International Airport were driven in a state of quiet anticipation.</p>

<p>Just over a month ago, Kylie, or Tang as she’s better known on the trail, was standing atop Mt. Katahdin deep in the wilderness of central Maine. She had just finished hiking the Appalachian Trail, the last of the three long trails she needed to complete one of the most prestigious achievements in the world of thru-hiking: The Triple Crown. Alongside her stood her partner Adam, or Chipotle as he’s known on trail. He had completed his Triple Crown less than a year before and came to join Kylie for the last few hundred miles of her effort. It was a moment neither of them would ever forget, and now, a few weeks later, they were sitting in a dusty parking lot in Rhododendron outside the venue of the Triple Crown Ceremony, the magnificent Mt. Hood standing proudly in the distance.</p>

<h4 id="thru-hiking-is-hard">Thru-hiking Is Hard</h4>

<p>Thru-hiking has a reputation of being a sport for misfits, and if you boil it down to its component parts, it’s a wonder that anybody chooses to do it at all. Who would want to carry a bunch of heavy equipment on their back and then trek into the wilderness for weeks on end? Such a person would spend all day sweating up steep inclines and pulverizing their knees on meandering descents. They’d get drenched in the rain and they’d shiver in the snow. They’d have to ration food and filter all of their water – that is, whenever they could find it. And at the end of the day, they wouldn’t get to shower and sleep in a soft bed. No, they’d crawl into a dirty sleeping bag and sleep in their accrued daily dirt and sweat on the hard ground. Oh, and did I mention that there are no bathrooms out in the wilderness? Even something as simple as relieving oneself turns into work, something to be planned and executed.</p>

<p>Indeed, many people who attempt thru-hiking promptly give up! Nearly a third of those who start the Appalachian Trail with full intent to stand on top of Mt. Katahdin themselves quit within the first 100 miles, and another third quit within the first 500. And yet, there remains the few that do make it all the way to Maine. These are members of a subculture that lives to live outside. When they’re on the trail, they feel alive. When they’re not, they’re thinking about when they will be back on the trail.</p>

<h4 id="trail-names">Trail Names</h4>

<p>Kylie and Adam are squarely in this latter group, as are the others in attendance at the Triple Crown Ceremony. Of course, in these circles, Kylie and Adam go by their trail names: Tang and Chipotle. A trail name is a funny, sacred thing. One’s given name is for the real world, but on trail, the real world is so distant that it may as well be ancient Mesopotamia. Out on trail one needs a different name for different circumstances. Trail names can be anything, but usually, they are bestowed by a companion who notices some personality quirk or witnesses some funny or strange happening. The aptly monikered Chipotle earned his title from his love of the chain restaurant of the same name. Chipotle estimates that he’s eaten Chipotle no less than 2000 times, and every time a new store opens up he is one of the first to try it out.</p>

<p>Other trail names aren’t so obvious. The origin of Tang’s trail name remains a mystery to most of those who know her, and she likes it that way. Shades, Sticks, Boomerang, All-You-Can-Eat, Double-Stuff, Longfish, Church, Thoroughbred, Scab, and Dirty-Girl are all names that invite speculation of epics and comedies. Kylie and Adam were happy to be in this room, among these people, and with them felt a deep sense of camaraderie. These people all get each other. They’ve seen what’s out there in the wilderness, and they understand why it’s worth pursuing.</p>

<h4 id="the-science-behind-walking">The Science Behind Walking</h4>

<h5 id="some-famous-walkers">Some Famous Walkers</h5>
<p>There is a long history of folks who found purpose along their walks in nature. Jean-Jaques Rousseau, Henry David Thoreau, William Wordsworth, Virginia Woolf, Charles Darwin, John Muir, and countless others discovered that walking through wilderness could be a source of inspiration and clarity – a way to not only know the world better, but to know oneself better, too.</p>

<h5 id="cognitive-health">Cognitive Health</h5>
<p>Reflect on your own life, dear reader. You yourself may have “gone on a walk to clear your head” or “taken a stroll to find room to think”. Indeed, there is a longstanding and important relationship between the mind and the feet that has become of scientific interest in recent years. Researchers have found that walking for as little as 90 minutes a week can decrease cognitive decline in elderly women, that walking for an hour on a treadmill prior to a divergent thinking test improved creativity scores by 60%, and that regular periods of walking can even increase the volume of the hippocampus, the brain’s memory center. The fact that walking, a simple, non-cognitive task, has such a wealth of benefits for our brain health is on its surface quite surprising. However, the story begins to make much more sense when we consider our ancient ancestors.</p>

<h5 id="evolutionary-biology">Evolutionary Biology</h5>
<p>Evolutionary biologists have much to say on walking and the brain, and many have gone so far as to credit our bipedalism as a necessary precursor to our high intelligence. The use of two legs rather than four, the thinking goes, resulted in two important changes in our evolutionary history: the development of our hands and more efficient ambulation. The development of hands entailed the development of complex manipulation – the exact kind of skill that required the use of cortical tissue, the brain matter associated with complex thought and reasoning. Additionally, more efficient ambulation meant that excess energy could be devoted to the brain rather than musculature.</p>

<p>Together, these changes formed a virtuous cycle. As our brains grew, we developed new skills and tools, like hunting and language. As our skills and tools developed, our species developed more efficient methods of collecting and storing resources. An excess amount of resources meant more energy could be devoted to the brain and its development. And so on. Summed up by the evolutionary biologist Mary Leaky,</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“One cannot overemphasize the role of bipedalism in hominid development. It stands as perhaps the salient point that differentiates the forebears of man from other primates. This unique ability freed the hands for myriad possibilities - carrying, tool-making, intricate manipulation. From this single development, in fact, stems all modern technology. Somewhat oversimplified, the formula holds that this new freedom of forelimbs posed a challenge. The brain expanded to meet it. And mankind was formed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="a-way-of-life">A Way of Life</h4>

<p>Of course, none of this was on the minds of Kylie or Adam as they traded trail stories with the other Triple Crowners in that stuffy room in Rhododendron. Their brains may have benefited from the thousands of miles they spent on the trail, but brain health wasn’t ever on the list of reasons why they chose to hike thousands and thousands of miles. To them, being on trail was a way of life, something that was deeply challenging and fulfilling, something that simply wasn’t available in their day-to-day lives back home.</p>

<p>Thru-hiking engenders a clarity of purpose that has become all-too-rare in the modern world. When you wake in the morning nestled in your sleeping bag, early morning sun illuminating your colorful nylon cocoon, there is a very clear idea of what needs to be done, and that simplifies life to a delightful degree. What will you eat today? Whatever you have in your bag. How far will you walk? However far you need to go.  Who will you walk with? Whoever is walking in the same direction you are. Beyond these questions remain a few points of uncertainty, such as the afternoon weather or the quality of trail in the upcoming national forest, but life on the trail takes on a quality of streamlined unity – something notably lacking in much of modernity. As observed by the author Rebecca Solnit over twenty years ago:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Many people nowadays live in a series of interiors - home, car, gym, office, shops - disconnected from each other. On foot everything stays connected, for while walking one occupies the spaces between those interiors in the same way one occupies those interiors. One lives in the whole world rather than in interiors built up against it.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="the-triple-crown-ceremony">The Triple Crown Ceremony</h4>

<p>There were a series of guest speakers that afternoon in Rhododenron. Apple Pie, a well-known thru-hiker kicked things off with a few words of congratulations to the newest Triple Crowners, then she shared a personal anecdote from her time spent on the CDT. She described how she had lost her toilet paper right out of town just before a very remote part of the trail, so she had to use rocks to wipe herself for three days before finally encountering another hiker who mercifully donated some of his supplies to her. Adam laughed hard, though he had heard the story once before when he and Apple Pie hiked a leg of the AT together.</p>

<p>Later, a woman named Fidget spoke about her seven year hike from the southernmost tip of South America to the northernmost tip of North America - a 22,000 mile epic filled with stories of terror, compassion, and triumph. She shared a story of how she met a man in a small village as she hiked through Peru. He had taken a liking to her and offered his bread to take for her journey. However, she had learned earlier that the village was so poor that a loaf of bread was equivalent to an entire day’s worth of food. Not wanting him to starve over her, she refused his offer, believing that it was the most respectful action she could take, and the man accepted her decision with kindness. Her story was powerful, moving some to tears, but it was by no means unique. Each and every one of the hikers in the room that day had their own stories, their own experiences, their own lessons learned, but most would never be shared outside the circles of a few close friends and hiking partners.</p>

<h4 id="now-what">Now What?</h4>

<p>The Appalachian Trail is 2,200 miles long starting in Georgia and ending in Maine. The Pacific Crest Trail is 2,600 miles long starting in California and ending in Washington. The Continental Divide Trail is 3,100 miles long starting in New Mexico and ending in Montana. Together, they add up to nearly 8,000 miles in length. It takes some people their whole lives to complete the Triple Crown, while others make the (insane) attempt to complete it in a single year. Regardless of pace, it is an unbelievably impressive achievement, and it is no wonder that fewer than 700 people to date have officially completed it – about as many people who have been to space. At the conclusion of the ceremony, small wooden plaques were awarded to 2023’s batch of Triple Crowners – a tiny trophy next to the enormity of their achievement. Adam and Kylie have their plaques displayed next to each other on a shelf in their home. After such a massive achievement, I wondered what could be next for the two of them. Could they have quenched their thirst for adventure? I was happy to learn that the answer was a decisive no. Kylie plans on running 250 miles in three days in Arizona, and Adam wants to thru-hike the 500 mile-long Colorado Trail in 11 days. I wish both of them luck, and I look forward to the stories they bring back from these adventures.</p>

<figure>  
  <img class="center" src="../assets/img/blog/adam-and-kylie.png" alt="Adam (Chipotle) and Kylie (Tang)" />
  <figcaption>Adam (Chipotle) and Kylie (Tang)</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning" /><published>2022-12-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/grounded-cognition-and-rl"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="grounded-cognition-and-reinforcement-learning">Grounded Cognition and Reinforcement Learning</h1>

<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>

<p>Grounded cognition as we know it today was born out of a reaction against the early to middle 20th century psychological view of cognition as an amodal system of symbolic representation and manipulation. However, grounded cognition has in fact been the dominant view of cognition for most of recorded history and extends back to ancient philosophers like Epicurus (Barsalou, 1999, J. Prinz 2002, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). From the perspective of grounded cognition, it is unlikely that the brain contains amodal symbols. Further, if it does happen to contain amodal symbols, they must work together with modal representations to create cognition (Barsalou, 2008). Instead, the grounded perspective stresses an emphasis on the interactions between perception, action, the body, the environment, and other agents, typically during goal achievement. The mechanisms by which cognition operates within these interactions include simulation, situated action, and bodily states. The emphasis on agent, environment, goal achievement, and situated action positions grounded cognition as particularly suitable to modeling using reinforcement learning, a computational approach focused on goal-directed learning through interaction (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). Indeed, grounded cognition and reinforcement learning are a natural pairing, with evidence from the former being largely accounted for by the theoretical outlook of the latter. In what follows we describe reinforcement learning, discuss theories of grounded cognition in that context, and then step through evidence presented in Barsalou’s Grounded Cognition (Barsalou, 2008).</p>

<h4 id="reinforcement-learning">Reinforcement Learning</h4>

<p>Reinforcement learning (RL) is a computational approach to learning from interaction, and is commonly used in machine learning and robotics (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). In a nutshell, RL is learning what to do so as to maximize a reward signal. It is characterized by two distinguishing properties: trial-and-error search, and delayed reward. That is, the agent does not know what actions to take in advance but must discover them by trial and error, and similarly, the agent does not know how rewarding its actions will be or how rewards may aggregate over time. Thus, it must consider the known and unknown, as well as delayed and immediate rewards.</p>

<p>The conflict between immediate and delayed rewards presents a primary challenge for RL: the tradeoff between exploration and exploitation. How can an agent balance between behaviors it knows are rewarding versus exploring for new behaviors that may be potentially more (or less) rewarding? This exploitation-exploration tradeoff is another key feature of RL. The following components constitute an RL model: a policy, a reward function, a value function, and (optionally) a model of the environment (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). An agent’s policy maps perceived states of the environment to actions that can be taken in those states and psychologically corresponds to a set of stimulus-response rules. Its reward function maps each perceived state-action pair to a reward (immediate rewards). Its value function represents the total amount of reward an agent can expect to accumulate over the future from its current state (long-term rewards). An agent uses its model of the environment (model) and bodily state to determine a set of potential actions to take (policy). It then chooses an action to take based on consideration of both immediate (reward function) and long-term (value function) rewards.</p>

<p>What makes RL unique to other computational learning approaches is that it characterizes a learning problem rather than a method (Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998). This shift in focus inherently encapsulates an agent, its motivation, and its environment, making it amenable to the grounded view of cognition.</p>

<h4 id="grounded-cognition">Grounded Cognition</h4>

<p>There are several theories of grounded cognition, each capturing different aspects of how humans operate within the world. Each theory builds off the importance of simulation, situated action, and bodily states.</p>

<p>First, we consider cognitive linguistics theories, which assert that people possess extensive knowledge of their bodies and experiences. Abstract concepts draw upon this knowledge metaphorically. To demonstrate, consider the ubiquitous use of concrete metaphors to discuss abstract concepts across cultures (e.g., happiness is associated with “up” and sadness with “down”) (Lakoff &amp; Johnson, 1980, 1999, as cited in Barsalou, 2008).</p>

<p>Second, there are theories of situated action, which focus on the central roles of perception and action in cognition. These theories place emphasis on the tight coupling of environment, goal achievement, and social interaction, which engender a focus on dynamic systems rather than computational architectures that only manipulate symbols.</p>

<p>Both classes of theories align with RL, where learning and behavior is undertaken by a goal-directed agent within an environment. Note that the agents we are concerned with are humans who operate as social creatures within a social environment and consequently have social goals. A final class of theories are those of cognitive simulation, which can be subdivided into perceptual symbol systems, memory theories, and social simulation theories. Perceptual symbol systems integrate traditional symbolic systems with grounded cognition via simulation of symbol manipulation (i.e., you can internally imagine and manipulate symbols to which you have previously been exposed). Grounded memory theories originated out of the belief that past theories of memory have focused too much on passive storage and not enough on situated action. Glenberg proposed that memory primarily serves to control situated action, and that stored memories reflect bodily actions and their ability to mesh with goal pursuit (Glenberg, 1997, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Social simulation theories offer a grounded view of interpersonal interaction. It is argued that theory of mind – where one infers another’s internal state – is achieved through the representation of another’s mind by simulating one’s own. Relatedly, mirror neurons are an interesting component of social cognition, as they fire when we perceive an action taken by another person. Importantly, mirror neurons respond to the goal of the action, not the action itself, which echoes the RL focus on goal-directed learning and behavior.</p>

<p>Indeed, all these cognitive simulation theories can be represented in the RL framework as an agent’s policy and reward/value function, where the agent simulates the potential actions available to it and assigns rewards to those actions prior to choosing one. Further, if we take Glenberg’s view of stored memories as primarily to control situated action, then we can consider the memories of the agent to be the learning resulting from the RL process. As actions are taken, memory (policy) is updated to reflect its outcome (reward function/ value function). From a theoretical view, this is a nice start on mapping grounded cognition to RL, but how does this mapping hold up with empirical findings?</p>

<h4 id="relation-to-empirical-findings">Relation to Empirical Findings</h4>

<p>There has been much work showing how simulation, situations, and bodily states play central roles in cognition. In the domain of perception and action, results show that perception of the world influences which actions are perceived to be available, and, conversely, the actions perceive as available influence how the world is perceived. States of perception get stored in memory, and are later triggered when similar stimuli are presented, which produces perceptual inferences that go beyond what is perceived, a useful mechanism for determining how best to act in a familiar situation (Goldstone, 1995; Hanson, 2006 as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Relatedly, as visual objects are perceived, simulations of potential actions become active in preparation for situated action. Indeed, even perception of space is shaped by how the body may act within it (Franklin &amp; Tversky, 1990, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). The intertwined relationship between perception and action reflects the stimulus-response pairs available to an agent. Note that perception here includes internal states (i.e., perception includes simulation). In the RL framework, the policy reflects an agent’s current state (perception) and its potential choices (actions). In the grounded view, one’s policy would be under continuous revision as the world and new behavior is explored. However, one’s attention would align accordingly with the policy most suitable to the situation, thereby biasing perception towards the elements relevant to that policy. This accounts for the perceptual distortion within the perception-action (stimulus-response) cycle.</p>

<p>With respect to memory, both implicit and explicit memory have been shown to heavily rely on multimodal simulations of previous episodes (Roediger &amp; McDermott, 1993; Schacter et al., 2004; Paivio, 1971, 1986; Conway, 1990, 2002; Rubin, 2006, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Simulations of stimuli held in implicit memory improve perceptual fluency and increase the likelihood of correct categorization of subsequent stimuli. Simulation within explicit memory appears central to constructing future events from past events. Working memory has been shown to be maintained by simulations of absent stimuli. Further, when stimuli is relevant to visual imagery, the motor system becomes engaged, suggesting that the salience of the simulation is related to how our bodies may use it to act (Barsalou, 2008). We can map the grounded view of memory onto the RL concept of policy (again), where an agent uses past experiences as a mapping between perception and action. By simulating past experiences (implicitly or explicitly) we bias our attention to what we believe will be important to achieve our goals (implicit or explicit) given our current state. Successfully doing so results in improved performance, whereas unsuccessful attention may result in surprise and subsequently a larger policy (memory/belief) update.</p>

<p>While simulation in memory has been accepted for many years, simulation as the basis of knowledge representation is still considered a radical proposal (Barsalou, 2008). However, even here there is evidence for the grounded view of cognition. There has been work demonstrating that properties are more difficult to describe as they become larger, and that many detailed properties are difficult to verbalize. Both findings indirectly support the idea that we simulate objects and their properties to verify them (Solomon &amp; Barsalou, 2004; Morison &amp; Tversky, 1997, as cited in Barsalou, 2008). Additionally, lesion damage to different parts of the brain results in the loss of conceptual categories. For example, damage to the visual cortex results in the loss of the animal categories, as we categorize animals by their visual properties. Similarly, damage to the motor cortex results in the loss of tools, as we categorize tools by how we use them with our bodies. Everything we know about the world is stored in our brains, and the RL mechanism by which knowledge is updated is through exploration and exploitation, action and reward, and the environmental state and goal-pursuit. It stands to reason that the knowledge we learn is tightly coupled within the context in which it was learned, which includes how we came to learn it, including the brain regions involved in our learning. However, this connection is somewhat tenuous, as RL intentionally avoids the concept of knowledge on its own and is instead focused on the learning problem as a whole. One might make the argument that knowledge is encapsulated within the notion of policy, but it is not explicit. Indeed, one of the reasons RL seems to be so successful is that it does not attempt to nail down what knowledge is, but rather how an agent learns in an environment to achieve a goal.</p>

<h4 id="simulation">Simulation</h4>

<p>In what has been discussed, we can notice a pattern emerging. Simulation is the mechanism in grounded cognition by which agents make sense and act within world, which consists of a body and environment. Further, perception of the world is contingent on the simulations maintained by the agent and is often biased towards available action choices. This relationship between state and action is well captured by the notion of policy within RL. As we consider other findings found in grounded cognition, we find again and again the suitability of RL to explain them. Take the domain of language comprehension. The meaning of language is simulated using situation models, which represent information with spatial properties (Barsalou, 2008). In other words, readers comprehend text by simulating what they read. Findings show that reading an action word activates the motor system. Similarly, readers simulate affect (emotional states) during comprehension. If we take the goal of reading to be comprehension, then comprehension can be thought of as the successful recall and integration of the meanings of the words. To that extent, RL is perfectly suitable to explain language comprehension (although the process itself would happen very rapidly). The policy (stimulus-response) would consist of rapid choices (likely unconsciously made) of integrating the meaning of language into one’s internal representation (or situation model). The reward function would be the immediate comprehensibility of one’s internal representation after integration of the most recent language, and the value function would be represented as the cohesiveness of the meaning of the overall thrust of the complete message communicated. The flexibility of RL can be used to extend to all sorts of phenomena in grounded cognition. In the domain of thought, physical reasoning relies on simulations of physical situations, suggesting that past experiences inform the understanding and reasoning of the current physical world (i.e., the policy has updated to inform current state-action choices). Mental model theory is used to explain abstract reasoning, and there is evidence that simulation plays a key role. Additionally, social cognition relies on simulation (that’s what empathy is!). In each case (language comprehension, thought, and social cognition), the problem can be broken down and represented as an RL model. The policy consists of choice-action pairs based on past experiences and the current environment, while the goal is defined as successful comprehension, or reasoning, or social connection, and the reward reflects the success of the interpretation, thinking, or communicating towards achieving its respective goal.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>Reinforcement learning is well-suited to explain the theories and evidence prominent in grounded cognition, but there are still some gaps to address. First, as mentioned earlier, there is no explicit definition of what knowledge is within RL. In my view, this is no problem, as knowledge is captured within the notion of policy (in a functional sense). However, it may be desirable to extend a version of RL to make a concrete definition of knowledge. Another gap to address would be the disconnect between the sequential processing of RL and the inherently dynamic, parallel, noisy processes of the grounded view of cognition, where environment and agent mutually interact with and influence each other in multiple and simultaneous ways. Perhaps the solution here is not to modify RL, but to parallelize it! Cognition is composed of myriad parallel processes, and if they can each be accounted for by an RL framework, perhaps extending the range and number of RL algorithms is the way forward. Finally, as a direction for further investigation, it would be interesting to see how the explore-exploit tradeoff is accounted for from the grounded perspective. In (Daw et al., 2006), a majority of gamblers explored new slot machines to play. How would this result hold up for decisions that have higher stakes, like choosing a spouse, trekking through unknown territory, or playing high-stakes poker? Grounded cognition and RL may offer the means to explore these problems.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<p>Barsalou, L. W. (2008). Grounded cognition. Annual Review of Psychology, 59, 617–645. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.59.103006.093639</p>

<p>Daw, N. D., O’Doherty, J. P., Dayan, P., Seymour, B., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2006). Cortical substrates for exploratory decisions in humans. Nature, 441(7095), 876–879. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04766</p>

<p>Sutton, R. S., &amp; Barto, A. G. (1998). Reinforcement Learning Chap 2. MIT Press, 465(1), 90–94. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20351022</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analytic vs Holistic Traditions of Thought</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/individual-diff-cas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analytic vs Holistic Traditions of Thought" /><published>2022-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/individual-diff-cas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/individual-diff-cas"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="analytic-vs-holistic-traditions-of-thought">Analytic vs Holistic <br />Traditions of Thought</h1>

<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>

<p>Aside from the planet we live on and certain biological processes, the one thing all human beings have in common is diversity. There are no two people who are the same on this earth, and, similarly, no two cultures are the same. Our cultures collectively store the awesome wealth of human achievement, including our great discoveries, our great stories, and our collective triumph in surviving long enough to look back and appreciate the wake of history trailing behind us. It is a relatively recent development that psychology has begun to recognize how deeply our cultural heritage can influence the ways in which we interact with the world.</p>

<p>In their paper, Culture and Systems of Thought: Holistic Versus Analytic Cognition (Nisbett et al., 2001), Nisbett et al. investigate cognitive differences between modern denizens of far Eastern cultures (i.e., Chinese, Japanese, and Korean) and Western cultures (i.e., American), which have respectively inherited the core of their intellectual traditions from ancient Chinese and Greek cultures. Holistic cognition was born of ancient Chinese culture, which, as a predominantly agricultural society in which vast numbers of people worked together to produce food, placed strong value on harmony, interdependence, and the oneness of all things. Analytic cognition originated from ancient Greece, which, being an individualistic society of shepherds, fishermen, and tradesmen, placed a high value on autonomy, debate, and logic. Today, these two forms of cognition have resulted in substantial differences in certain cognitive processes between Western (Analytic) and far Eastern (Holistic) people.</p>

<p>The mode of cognition one inherits biases the attention to, and the subsequent interpretation of, the experience of the world around them, resulting in measurable differences between people who come from different traditions. In this essay, we discuss the differences between analytic and holistic cognition by grounding them in the findings discussed in (Nisbett et al., 2001) and then analyze three cognitive domains where these differences manifest: concept representation, analogy, and symbol use.</p>

<h4 id="eastern-vs-western-cognition">Eastern vs Western Cognition</h4>

<p>As proposed by Nisbett et al., the social organization of society has an enormous effect on the cognition of the citizens within it. Social organization biases attention to certain aspects of the field at the expense of others, and what is attended to influences beliefs about the world. Consequently, beliefs about the world guide what is believed to be important and how knowledge can be obtained, which in turn dictates the development and application of certain cognitive processes at the expense of others (Nisbett et al., 2001). In a nutshell, social organization affects cognitive processes in two ways: indirectly by focusing attention on different parts of the environment and directly by making some kinds of social communication patterns more acceptable than others. This can differentially affect the intellectual trajectory of a society.</p>

<p>Indeed, the Greeks held the outlook of objects having their own properties, which in turn led to advancements like surgery and geometry. The Chinese saw the world as utterly interrelated which led to an early system of irrigation and the correct conclusion of why the tides rose and fell. In modern day experiments, numerous differences in cognitive processes between Easterners and Westerners have been found. Easterners attend to the entire perceptual field more than Westerners, who attend more to a salient object within the field. Westerners benefit more from perceived control and are more subject to the illusion of control. Easterners’ explanations of things involve situational factors more than their Western counterparts. They also consider a broader range of potential explanations, resulting in less surprise and predisposition to hindsight bias (the tendency to regard events as having been inevitable in retrospect). Westerners tend to explain events with respect to a target object and its properties, making them more prone to fundamental attribution error, that is, the tendency to attribute behavior to dispositions of a person and to slight the role of situations and context.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><i><u>Note</u>: the Western tendency to fall for the illusion of control as well as the fundamental attribution error makes for an interesting combination when considered alongside the modern atmosphere of rampant anxiety in the Western world. Not only do Westerners assume control exists where it does not, but they assume the failure to control is the fault of a person rather than a fact of the situation.</i></p>
</blockquote>

<p>When it comes to categorization, Easterners group objects and events on the basis of functional relationships whereas Westerners group them on the basis of category membership. The list goes on. Easterners prefer to seek compromise, rely more on experiential knowledge, and heavily rely on prior beliefs. Westerners are less likely to seek compromise, tend to reject one or both of two propositions that could be construed as contradictory, and are more capable of setting aside prior beliefs, as they rely more on logical reasoning. As we will see, these differences have profound implications for cognitive processes traditionally understood in a Western context.</p>

<h4 id="concept-representation">Concept Representation</h4>

<p>Concept representation is a domain where differences between the holistic and analytical modes of cognition become quite stark. Take the notion of conceptual coherence. According to Murphy and Medin, “concepts are coherent to the extent that they fit people’s background knowledge or naïve theories about the world. These theories help to relate the concepts in a domain and to structure the attributes that are internal to a concept (Murphy &amp; Medin, 1985).” Immediately we see how the holistic and analytical modes of cognition might result in completely different conceptual structures for the same stimuli. If conceptual coherence depends on both background knowledge and beliefs about the world, then analytical cognition would result in concepts that are oriented towards objects and their properties, whereas holistic cognition would result in concepts focused on the relationships between objects in the field.</p>

<p>Murphy and Medin describe the theories of conceptual coherence based on the following strategies: similarity, feature correlations, and categorization. For each strategy, there is a different perspective for the holistic and analytic modes. For similarity, an analytic thinker would focus on the properties of objects as the indicator of similarity, whereas a holistic thinker would focus on the functional relationship between objects. The same logic applies to categorization strategies. Similarly, for feature correlations, the most salient features to an analytic thinker would be those that are inherent to an object itself (e.g., grouping baby and mother in separate categories as one is a child and the other an adult). Holistic thinkers would instead attend to features that are most relevant to its functional relations (e.g., grouping baby and mother together since a mother is the caretaker of the baby). Murphy and Medin propose that the glue that binds up a conceptually coherent category is the role of theories. This conclusion seems particularly relevant to the current discussion. It is unlikely that a holistic and analytic thinker would arrive at the same conclusion for a conceptually coherent category, yet each thinker may be correct in their conclusion, as it is their respective theories of the world which differentiate them. To make a holistic remark, two definitions for the same concept may seem contradictory, but it doesn’t necessarily make either definition incoherent.</p>

<h4 id="analogy">Analogy</h4>

<p>Analogy is another cognitive process that operates differently between the analytic and holistic modes of cognition. In the structure-mapping theory presented in (Gentner, 1982), Gentner asserts that analogy essentially works as the mapping the structural relations of a base domain into a target domain. The base and target domain will be different based on the salience of features most relevant in the domains. Considering this view, we again see how the process of analogy would be different between holistic and analytic thinkers.</p>

<p>Consider the example of the solar system. An analytic thinker would preferentially think of each planet as a constituent of the solar system, where each planet has its own orbit around the sun. When all these pieces are put together, there you have the solar system. On the other hand, a holistic thinker would think of the solar system in the opposite direction, where the solar system exists as a single system of all the planets revolving around the sun, and that each planet depends on the system as a whole. Interestingly, despite the difference in perspective, the analogy appears to be apt for mapping to similar cases from either perspective. Regardless of how the concept of solar system was construed, if the relations of the solar system map neatly into another domain (e.g., the structure of an atom), then the approach shouldn’t matter. While this applies to physical systems, it is likely a different story for social ones. Consider the domain of law, which is very different between West (contractual, permanent) and East (situational, flexible). Analogies in these domains are unlikely to translate neatly between cultures, as they are culturally dependent.</p>

<h4 id="symbols">Symbols</h4>

<p>A third domain of cognitive processing to compare the holistic and analytic modes of cognition is that of symbols. According to Andy Clark, language itself is a cognition-enhancing animal-built structure, which makes it not a means to express cognition, but rather an aspect of cognition itself (Clark, 2006). He argues that “by materializing thought in words, we create structures that are themselves proper objects of perception, manipulation, and (further) thought.” Consider the English writing system used in Western cultures. There is an alphabet composed of twenty-six characters, each with its own name and sound. Words are composed of characters when they are put together in certain, correct orders. Words are put together in a certain order to form sentences, and so on. Now, consider the writing system used in China, where there are over 10,000 characters! Each character has a unique meaning depending on the markings that make it up. Characters represent entities or actions rather than individual sounds. This distinction echoes that of the differences between analytic and holistic cognition.</p>

<p>Clark would argue that each symbolic system, English and Chinese, not only work differently as systems of writing, but so too do they differ in how cognition operates through their usage. To demonstrate, consider the fact that many languages have words with no suitable translation for a foreign tongue. For example, the Japanese word satori has no adequate English translation, and is in fact translated in numerous ways, including enlightenment, sudden awakening, flash of insight, etc. This is some evidence supporting Clark’s claim that language itself is an aspect of cognition rather than merely a vehicle for expressing cognition. From this perspective, holistic and analytic thinkers are likely working with language in completely different ways, which really makes one think just how different it must be to exist as a person from a different intellectual tradition than the one they were raised in.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>In this essay we have discussed the role of culture in cognition, the differences between analytic and holistic cognition, and the implications these differences have in interpreting cognitive processes traditionally understood in a Western context. Note that the differences laid out here are stark, as the Eastern and Western intellectual traditions are particularly distinct (a clever and intentional choice made by Nisbett et al. to demonstrate their point). Keep in mind that many more cultures exist outside of these two intellectual traditions. The point here is to demonstrate that differences exist rather than to pin down exactly which differences exist for everyone. What is clear is that cognitive processes are deeply intertwined with the social and environmental context in which they develop, and that there can be no clear separation between process and content when it comes to cognition (Nisbett et al., 2001). However, now that psychology and other sciences have begun to recognize these facts, much work needs to be done to extend existing models of cognitive processes to encompass this broader view of humanity.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<p>Clark, A. (2006). Language, embodiment, and the cognitive niche. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 10(8), 370–374. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2006.06.012</p>

<p>Gentner, D. (1982). Gentner_Structure Mapping. Cognitive Science, 7(2), 155–170. file://localhost/Volumes/alexvanvenrooij 1/Elektronische Artikelen/Papers/Unknown/2004-34.pdf</p>

<p>Murphy, G. L., &amp; Medin, D. L. (1985). The Role of Theories in Conceptual Coherence. Psychological Review, 92(3), 289–316. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.92.3.289</p>

<p>Nisbett, R. E., Choi, I., Peng, K., &amp; Norenzayan, A. (2001). Culture and systems of thought: Holistic versus analytic cognition. Psychological Review, 108(2), 291–310. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.108.2.291</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Attention Crisis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/attention-crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Attention Crisis" /><published>2022-05-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/attention-crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/attention-crisis"><![CDATA[<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" href="../assets/css/blogstyles.css" />
</head>

<h1 id="our-attention-crisis">Our Attention Crisis</h1>

<h4 id="the-current-situation">The Current Situation</h4>

<p>We are living through an attention crisis. Despite all the progress we have made as a society, it seems we have lost our ability to focus. A study in 2014 found that the average college student switches tasks every 65 seconds [19]. Almost as bleak for office workers, another study found they only remain focused for about three minutes before switching tasks [6]. What’s going on here? In an age where people have a portal in their pocket to all human knowledge, where a wealth of information about nearly any obstacle can be accessed almost instantaneously, it would stand to reason that we should be more focused, not less. But, of course, nothing is so simple.</p>

<p>The information age has given rise to an unprecedented amount of content. For example, as of February 2020, more than 500 hours of video were uploaded to YouTube every minute [10]. The sheer quantity of content available online is far more than any one person could hope to meaningfully engage with. For the individual, this situation presents a need for effective navigation through a ceaselessly expanding ocean of information. For the purveyors of content, the challenge becomes attracting and holding attention. Some services accomplish this by providing quality content to their users in exchange for a subscription fee (e.g., Netflix), while others, like Facebook and YouTube, generate revenue through advertisements. This advertising model is most profitable when it captures as much time as possible from as many people as possible. To that end, these attention merchants (a term coined by Tim Wu in his book The Attention Merchants [18]) have discovered, developed, and deployed an array of tactics to distract us and gobble up our time, often using unethical practices.</p>

<p>In a world with so many things competing for our attention, we must stop and ask ourselves: what is it that we are paying attention to? William James, the American psychologist and father of pragmatism, once said,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“My experience is what I agree to attend to. Only those items which I notice shape my mind.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At the end of our days, when we look back at our lives, we will remember our experience as the composition of all we attended to over the years. Simply put, the brief time we have on Earth is precious. Is it ethical to allow an entire industry to exploit our attention and consume our lives to increase their quarterly earnings? What can we do as individuals to better protect our attention and devote it to the things we find meaningful in our own lives? Whatever the answers may be, to adequately address either of these questions we must first understand how attention works.</p>

<h4 id="the-attentional-bottleneck">The Attentional Bottleneck</h4>

<p>The concept of attention has captivated some of our deepest thinkers throughout the ages. Today, it is a crucial area of investigation in many domains, such as education, psychology, and neuroscience. Attention can be conceptualized in many ways. Here, we define it as the behavioral and cognitive process of allocating limited cognitive resources by selectively concentrating on discrete aspects of information while ignoring other perceivable information. Effective allocation of cognitive resources is crucial, as the amount of information impinging on our senses far exceeds our processing capabilities, resulting in an attentional bottleneck. To illustrate, in human vision, less than 1% of available visual input information can enter the bottleneck, leading to a phenomenon known as inattentional blindness [16]. Indeed, vision and attention are closely linked (even mind-wandering, where internal attention has refocused on task irrelevant stimuli, can be predicted from eye movements [2]). Consequently, much of the research related to attention has placed an emphasis on visual attention.</p>

<p>There are two general models of visual attention. The first is known as the spotlight model, and it was inspired by the work of William James [8]. This model describes attention as having three parts: a focus, a margin, and a fringe. The focus of attention is high resolution, the center of which being where attention is directed. The focus is surrounded by a low-resolution zone called the fringe, which is then circumscribed by the margin of attention, or where attention is completely absent. The second model of visual attention is called the zoom lens model, and it inherits all the properties of the spotlight model with the added property of the focus changing in size [3] (similar to how a zoom lens on a camera works). The zoom lens feature accounts for the attentional bottleneck by assuming that attentional resources are fixed. In this model, it follows that the larger the area of focus is, the slower the processing of that region will be since the fixed resource is distributed over a larger area.</p>

<h4 id="sifting-through-the-infinite-haystack">Sifting Through the Infinite Haystack</h4>

<p>The attentional bottleneck presents a challenge for us in the modern world. Today’s deluge of content is flooding our senses (and inboxes) at an unprecedented pace.  As observed by Herbert A. Simon back in 1971:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In an information-rich world, the wealth of information means a dearth of something else: a scarcity of whatever it is that information consumes. What information consumes is rather obvious: it consumes the attention of its recipients. Hence a wealth of information creates a poverty of attention and a need to allocate that attention efficiently among the overabundance of information sources that might consume it [15].”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In other words, in our modern world of near infinite content, a need has emerged to efficiently connect people with the proverbial needle in the haystack. The tech giant Google made its name and fortune by creating a solution to this problem in the form of a search engine, a feat so well done that to ‘google’ something is itself a verb meaning to search for something on the internet. Search engines are great for users who can describe what they are looking for. But what about the users who want to discover something new? For them, recommendation systems have been a boon. Recommendation systems, like their name implies, offer recommendations of new content to a user based on that user’s history, such as the content they have viewed in the past (e.g., YouTube), what they’ve purchased (e.g., Amazon), or how they write their emails (e.g., Gmail autocomplete).  These systems can conveniently connect people with new content that they may have never encountered on their own.</p>

<p>Unfortunately for these innovations, several ethical concerns have been raised about these systems. Some believe that they may be subtly guiding users into echo chambers, driving tribalism, and fracturing our shared culture [9]. Others think that these systems learn to exploit cognitive biases in people and manipulate them into making decisions they wouldn’t otherwise make (e.g., impulse buying) [1]. While considering these ethical issues, we should remember that these systems are tools meant to assist our attention and guide it to what we find interesting, which begs the question: what is our attention drawn to? That is, how is attention oriented in our environment?</p>

<h4 id="may-stimul-i-have-your-attention">May Stimul-I Have Your Attention?</h4>

<p>There are two kind of cues (or stimuli) that attract attention: endogenous (i.e., central/internal) and exogenous (i.e., peripheral/external) [14]. Endogenous attention is the intentional allocation of cognitive resources and is typically oriented to one’s goals or desires. This goal-driven, or “top-down,” attention can be manipulated by the demands of a task that aligns with one’s intentions. Conversely, exogenous attention is guided through external processes and is responsive to stimuli in one’s environment. A sudden loud noise or movement in a shadowy bush attracts attention in a non-volitional way – a useful feature for our ancient ancestors. This non-volitional, or “bottom-up,” attention is reflexive, automatic, and stimulus driven.</p>

<p>As mentioned before, the attentional bottleneck makes it essential to have an effective strategy to attend to the most important aspects of the world around us. Endogenous and exogenous orientation, respectively driven by internal and external cues, ideally help us strike a balance between the demands of our inner goals and the constraints of our external environment. If there are relatively few constraints in the environment (e.g., there are no lions chasing us, we can pay our bills, we are healthy, etc.), then we have more cognitive resources to devote to our personal goals.</p>

<p>Humans, being social creatures, also have a particular sensitivity to social cues. For a person living in the distant past, it was crucial to survival that they be accepted by their tribe. Social acceptance meant food, shelter, status, and the chance to reproduce. Social rejection, on the other hand, was dangerous, and perhaps even fatal. Though the stakes aren’t as high as they once were, the biological infrastructure still exists in us today, and we still care deeply about what others think of us. Our attention is deeply intertwined with this fact, and the stimuli from our social environment are particularly salient, which may be one reason why social media has taken such a firm hold on so many people today.</p>

<h4 id="social-media-attention-merchantspirates">Social Media: Attention Merchants/Pirates</h4>

<p>Social connection has been one of the greatest drivers of the internet’s popularity since the 1990’s, with companies like America Online (AOL) selling itself as a place to connect with anybody in the world who has an internet connection. In the early and mid-2000’s, social media services began appearing, such as Friendster, MySpace, and Facebook. These platforms made big promises to bring people together in online communities, thus making friendships and connections possible for people living all over the planet. Even better, they were going to provide this service –- at least on the surface –- free of charge.</p>

<p>As mentioned previously, platforms like Facebook are attention merchants. That is, they profit off the attention of their users by showing them advertisements. Facebook uses the illusion of social cues (e.g., the number of likes on a posted photo) and variable reward signals (e.g., randomly notifying users of their friend’s activity) to keep users coming back to check the platform and scroll through ads. Ironically, Facebook isn’t interested in social connections in the real world (what our social sensitivies developed for), because their goal is to maximize user engagement (i.e., people’s time and attention) with their platform. To an attention merchant like Facebook, people are products. They earn money from advertisers by delivering ads to eyeballs. The more ads they show and the more effective the advertising is, the more profitable they become. That is what they care about, because that is where the money is.</p>

<p>The fiscal interests of attention merchants are aligned with a two-pronged strategy: maximize engagement (i.e., time spent in the platform), and deliver targeted advertisements. To these ends, an enormous amount of effort is taken to collect data from users, often without their knowledge or consent. This data is then used to train algorithms that maximize user engagement and deliver targeted ads, an ethically questionable practice termed surveillance capitalism [20]. It should be obvious that this strategy is not necessarily aligned with beneficence, as there is no consideration of whether it provides useful (or even accurate) content. Indeed, this mindset of engagement above all else is exemplified in Nir Eyal’s book Hooked: How to Build Habit-forming Products [4].</p>

<h5 id="broken-promises">Broken Promises</h5>

<p>What modern social media platforms have turned into is a far cry from their original promise of bringing people together. As has been pointed out by people like Tristan Harris and Aza Raskin in their film The Social Dilemma [13], this business strategy is likely causing serious harm to the fabric of society as we know it by driving polarization and proliferating misinformation, and it all starts with the exploitation of human attention. Worse still, the strategy of engagement above all else forces other industries to abide by the same rules. For example, news outlets have become more and more polarized since the advent of social media, as they are incentivized to sell stories that engage rather than stories that are true. Consider the findings of a 2018 study conducted at MIT which found that false news spreads six time faster than true news on the social media platform Twitter [17].</p>

<p>The fact that our information space has been corrupted by this business model of surveillance capitalism should alarm anybody, yet any meaningful reform currently seems remote. The problem is nuanced enough that it takes real technical knowledge to address it, something lacking in most of today’s politicians. Additionally, there is no incentive for the businesses themselves to change and every reason to maintain the status quo, as they are thriving in the current environment. So, what is there to do?</p>

<h4 id="what-do-we-do">What Do We Do?</h4>

<p>With the endless flood of content available to us and an array of powerful entities competing for our eyes, it seems very difficult to protect our attention and use it for our own interests. Fortunately, there are several ways that we as individuals can defend ourselves.</p>

<h5 id="education">Education</h5>

<p>The first step is education. People like Tristan Harris and Aza Raskin, who were once Silicon Valley insiders, have made great efforts to broadcast the severity of the situation to the public, and have even started the non-profit Center for Humane Technology. Nir Eyal, mentioned before for his book Hooked, wrote another book titled Indistractable: How to Control Your Attention and Choose Your Life [5], in which he offers some practical solutions to protect one’s attention (ostensibly from the exploitative practices that he helped proliferate). Johann Hari took a broader perspective on the attention crisis in his book Stolen Focus: Why You Can’t Pay Attention – and How to Think Deeply Again [7], where he considers a range of factors including social media, the modern diet, and our culture’s obsession with speed and convenience.</p>

<h5 id="device-management">Device Management</h5>

<p>There is no shortage of resources for understanding this problem and its potential solutions. However, while these may offer some useful advice for protecting our attention, they are focused primarily on exogenous factors. It certainly helps to disable notifications and to turn our phones to grayscale, but these address only the hook. What about when our attention has already been captured? Identifying when our attention has gone to a place that isn’t serving us and then reorienting it to something that is aligned with our interests takes a certain degree of self-awareness and executive functioning. Luckily, there is a way to cultivate these skills.</p>

<h5 id="mindfulness-practice">Mindfulness Practice</h5>

<p>Within the western psychological context, mindfulness is usually described as non-judgmental awareness of the present moment and is thought to entail paying attention with a certain attitude [12].  Training and refining attention skills are central to most conceptualizations of mindfulness practices, which often takes place during meditation [11]. Developing mindfulness skills positively impacts attentional functions by improving the allocation of attentional resources, specifically during early stages of processing [12]. A common form of mindfulness practice is to place attention on one’s breath for a fixed period (e.g., 10 minutes), and, when the mind inevitably wanders, to recognize where attention has gone and then return it to the breath non-judgmentally. Repeating this process over and over again develops an ability to recognize when attention has been unintentionally captured. Aside from the wealth of benefits that mindfulness practices offer, this one is particularly useful for protecting our attention from those who seek to prey upon it. Whereas disabling notifications is a form of exogenous defense, mindfulness can be considered a form of endogenous defense, training our executive functioning to recognize and reorient away from stimuli that have captured our attention but have nothing of substance to offer.</p>

<p>It should be noted that just because mindfulness practice can breed a form of equanimity with the world as it is, that doesn’t mean the world should not change. While we as individuals can use exogenous and endogenous defense strategies to protect our attention, we must ask ourselves whether the industries that seek to harvest our attention should be entitled to such power over us to begin with.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>Each of us has only a short time on Earth to do the things that we truly want to do, to live a life that is meaningful to us. This requires that we devote our time and attention to the things that matter most. But our attention, limited by the attentional bottleneck, can only be allocated to so many things. Attention merchants like Facebook further complicate the picture by exploiting our social sensitivities to attract and keep our attention to boost their bottom line. While human attention has been sought after for a long time, never has it been harvested at such a massive scale and with such impunity. Even though we as individuals can disable notifications on our phones and practice mindfulness to bolster our attentional defenses, there remain glaring ethical issues in the practices of some of today’s largest attention merchants. Despite their lucrative business model, systemic change is needed. To quote him once more, William James once said,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The moral flabbiness born of the exclusive worship of the bitch-goddess success. That – with the squalid cash interpretation put on the word ‘success’ – is our national disease.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We must ask whether these tech giants are successful in a way that is commensurate with the needs of society, or if they’re just rich from exploiting the society they’re embedded in. There is a world in which the technology we use helps us achieve our deeper goals rather than subverting them, but that is a world we must build together, and that will take a lot of attention.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<p>[1]	Adomavicius, G. et al. 2013. Do recommender systems manipulate consumer preferences? A study of anchoring effects. Information Systems Research. 24, 4 (2013), 956–975. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.2013.0497.</p>

<p>[2]	D’Mello, S.K. and Mills, C.S. 2021. Mind wandering during reading: An interdisciplinary and integrative review of psychological, computing, &amp; intervention research and theory. Language and Linguistics Compass: Cognitive Science of Lanuage. (2021).</p>

<p>[3]	Eriksen, C.W. and James, J.D.S. 1986. Visual attention within and around the field of focal attention. Perception &amp; Psychophysics. 40, 4 (1986), 225–240.</p>

<p>[4]	Eyal, N. 2014. Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products. Penguin Random House.</p>

<p>[5]	Eyal, N. 2019. Indistractable: How to Control Your Attention and Choose Your Life. BenBella Books, Inc.</p>

<p>[6]	González, V.M. and Mark, G. 1960. Managing Multiple Working Spheres “ Constant , Constant , Multi-tasking Craziness ”: Human Factors. 6, 1 (1960), 113–120.</p>

<p>[7]	Hari, J. 2022. Stolen Focus: Why You Can’t Pay Attention - and How to Think Deeply Again. Random House.</p>

<p>[8]	Hoffman, J.E. and Eriksen, C.W. 1972. Temporal and spatial characteristics of selective coding from visual displays. Perception &amp; Psychophysics. 12, August (1972), 201–204.</p>

<p>[9]	Hosanagar, K. et al. 2014. Will the global village fracture into tribes recommender systems and their effects on consumer fragmentation. Management Science. 60, 4 (2014), 805–823. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1287/mnsc.2013.1808.</p>

<p>[10]	Hours of video uploaded to YouTube every minute as of February 2020: 2022. https://www.statista.com/statistics/259477/hours-of-video-uploaded-to-youtube-every-minute/. Accessed: 2022-02-05.</p>

<p>[11]	Lutz, A. et al. 2008. Attention regulation and monitoring in meditation. Trends in Cognitive Sciences. 12, 4 (2008), 163–169. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2008.01.005.</p>

<p>[12]	Malinowski, P. 2013. Neural mechanisms of attentional control in mindfulness meditation. Frontiers in Neuroscience. 7, 7 FEB (2013), 1–11. DOI:https://doi.org/10.3389/fnins.2013.00008.</p>

<p>[13]	Orlowski, J. 2020. The Social Dilemma.</p>

<p>[14]	Posner, M.I. 1980. Orienting of attention. The Quarterly journal of experimental psychology. 32, 1 (1980), 3–25. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1080/00335558008248231.</p>

<p>[15]	Simon, H.A. 1971. Designing Organizations for an Information-Rich World. Computers, Communication, and the Public Interest. (1971), 37–72.</p>

<p>[16]	Simons, D.J. and Chabris, C.F. 1999. Gorillas in our midst: Sustained inattentional blindness for dynamic events. Perception. 28, 9 (1999), 1059–1074. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1068/p281059.</p>

<p>[17]	Vosoughi, S. et al. 2018. The Spread of True and False News Online. Science. 1151, March (2018), 1146–1151.</p>

<p>[18]	Wu, T. 2016. The Attention Merchants. Vintage Books.</p>

<p>[19]	Yeykelis, L. et al. 2014. Multitasking on a Single Device: Arousal and the Frequency, Anticipation, and Prediction of Switching Between Media Content on a Computer. Journal of Communication. 64, 1 (2014), 167–192. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1111/jcom.12070.</p>

<p>[20]	Zuboff, S. 2019. Surveillance Capitalism and the Challenge of Collective Action. New Labor Forum. 28, 1 (2019), 10–29. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1177/1095796018819461.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nick Hunkins</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>